<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remonstrance of the directors of the Netherlands East India Company presented to the Lords States Generall of the vnited Provinces, in defence of the said Companie, touching the bloudy proceedings against the English merchants, executed at Amboyna. Together, with the acts of the processe, against the sayd English. And the reply of the English East India Company, to the said remonstrance and defence. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Nederlandsche Oost-Indische Compagnie.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105421</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5711</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21088)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5711)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 781:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remonstrance of the directors of the Netherlands East India Company presented to the Lords States Generall of the vnited Provinces, in defence of the said Companie, touching the bloudy proceedings against the English merchants, executed at Amboyna. Together, with the acts of the processe, against the sayd English. And the reply of the English East India Company, to the said remonstrance and defence. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Nederlandsche Oost-Indische Compagnie.</author>
                  <author>East India Company.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 29, [3]; [2], 38; 47, [1] p., plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Dawson, for the East India Company,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴; ² A-E⁴; ³B-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>"An authentick copy of the confessions and sentences, against M. Tovverson, and complices .." has separate dated title page, pagination, and register. "A reply to the remonstrance of the bewinthebbers or directors of the Netherlands East-India Companie .." (caption title) has separate pagination and register beginning on ³B1.</note>
                  <note>¹E4 is blank. Variant: ¹E4 printed as title page, "An authentick copy of the acts of the processe against the English at Amboyna"; original title to part 2 is cancelled. This is the case with all copies of STC 7450a.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, ¹B1r has catchword "afore-"; ³B1r last line has "discouerie". Quire ¹A and part 2 are in the same setting as STC 7450a.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nederlandsche Oost-Indische Compagnie --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ambon (Indonesia) --  History --  Massacre, 1624 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5711:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5711:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A REMONSTRANCE OF THE DIRECTORS OF THE NETHERLANDS <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company, preſented to the <hi>Lords States Generall</hi> of the vnited Provinces, in defence of the ſaid Companie, touching the bloudy proceedings againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TOGETHER, <hi>With the Acts of the Proceſſe, againſt the ſayd</hi> ENGLISH.</p>
                  <p>AND <hi>The Reply of the</hi> Engliſh Eaſt India <hi>Company, to the ſaid Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance and Defence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
                  <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Iohn Dawſon,</hi> for the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company, 163<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5711:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5711:2"/>
                  <head>¶ <hi>To the Reader.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of the <hi>Netherlands Eaſt India</hi> Company, hereafter in the firſt place following, was by the ſame Company preſented to the <hi>Lord States Generall,</hi> of the vnited Provinces: in <hi>November, Anno 1624.</hi> for Anſwere of the Relation of the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt India</hi> Company, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vnjuſt, cruell, and barbarous proceeding againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and for juſtification of that infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous proceſſe, the Coppie of which Remonſtrance being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to the ſayd <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company, they forth with writ the ſubſequent Reply, and ſent the ſame to be preſented to the ſaid <hi>Lords States Generall,</hi> for a counter-poyſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt the ſaid Remonſtrance: At that time the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company intended not to have publiſht it in Print, thereby to make ſo many Iudges of the cauſe as now they muſt, but vpon faire hope then given them out of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> truſted (by the juſtice of the <hi>Lords States Generall,</hi> joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with that of their owne Soveraigne) to obtaine an iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of this cauſe, according to the merits thereof. But the Ambaſsadour of the ſaid <hi>Lords States</hi> being here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in <hi>Iune 1625.</hi> and moved by his Majeſtie for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the lives of his subjects, that were ſo treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly
<pb facs="tcp:5711:3"/>
but chered by theirs at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> as alſo for reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of their goods ſo made forfeit, and recompence for the damage of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company, by this and other acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vſed ſuch excuſe and cullor (as it ſeemeth out of the ground of this Remonſtrance: (which after many proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall diſputes finally concludeth for delay of tryall) that at the laſt, in <hi>September</hi> the ſame yeare, they obtained of his Majeſtie a reſpit of 18. moneths for the calling home of the Governour <hi>Harman van Speult,</hi> and the reſt of the Iudges in the ſayd bloudy proceſse, from out of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> to anſwere the matter here themſelues, and for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of all the other Complaints of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. To whom although this reſpit was irkeſome, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready borne ſo long delay, in a cauſe of ſuch impatient na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as alſo having a ſuſpition of the ſiniſter intent of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Companie: in this new reſpit; nevertheleſſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, that this was a favour craved by the ſaid <hi>Lords States</hi> in their firſt Ambaſſage to his Majeſtie, and their very congratulations of his happy ſucceſſe to his rightfull Crownes, they held it their duty to conforme themſelues to his Majeſties grace herein. As alſo the ſame <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company having confidence in the ſincere dealing of the <hi>Lords States Generall,</hi> whoſe Letter of the 31. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember. 1624.</hi> for calling home of the ſayd bloudy <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> and others, was committed to their conveyance, and by them ſent into the <hi>Indies,</hi> hoped that their remedy though ſlow and long, would yet at laſt be ſure, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo they put on a new patience, and expectation of ſome iſſue of this likely courſe. But having waited out this reſpit, which expired, ſome years now paſt, they finde all things fall out contrary to their hope ſo grounded vpon the <hi>Lords States</hi> promiſe and Letter, but altogether veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb facs="tcp:5711:3"/>
their ſuſpition of the drift of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany before mentioned. For the ſaid Letter of the <hi>Lords States</hi> being by the <hi>Engliſh Preſident</hi> at <hi>Iacatra,</hi> ſafely delivered to <hi>Carpentier, Governour Generall</hi> of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in the <hi>Indies,</hi> he (when <hi>Harman van Speult</hi> the late <hi>Governour</hi> of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and head of the bloudy treachery againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there) arrived at <hi>Iacatra</hi>) received him with great honour, yea with triumph, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſending him for <hi>Europe,</hi> to anſwere the complaints of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> according to the direction and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Lords States,</hi> by their ſayd Letter; made him cheife Commander of a fleete of ſhips, ſent from thence to <hi>Surat,</hi> and other Northerne parts of the <hi>Indies.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſident and Councell at <hi>Iacatra,</hi> in vaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting here-againſt, and vrging his remiſsion to <hi>Europe,</hi> in conſequence of the Letter of the <hi>Lords States</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd. Neither haue the Officers of the ſayd <hi>Netherlands</hi> Company in the <hi>Indies,</hi> in all that reſpit of 18 moneths, nor in all the time ſince, made any reſtitution or reparation to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as was promiſed and pretended, nor any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration thereunto, but rather haue added new grievances. So that it now plainely appeareth, that the ſayd <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands Eaſt India</hi> Company, in their earneſt ſuite to the <hi>Lords States,</hi> to procure his Majeſtie to giue reſpit for the due tryall of the cauſe of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> inſerted in the latter end of this enſuing Remonſtrance; intended nothing leſſe then ſuch a true tryall, but a cooling and blunting of the edge and zeale of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company, in purſuing of their due remedies, hoping (as it is in the fable of him, that vndertooke to teach the Aſſe to ſpeake) that in long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay and reſpit of time ſomething might happen, vtterly to elude and fruſtrate the reall performance: In the meane
<pb facs="tcp:5711:4"/>
time, beſides the goods of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that they detaine, they enioy the whole trade of the <hi>Mulluccoes, Banda,</hi> and <hi>Amboyna,</hi> the true, though wretched motive of their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable proceſse, againſt the Innocents, and haue raiſed the Nutmegs, Maces, Cloues, (being by this meanes ſolely in their owne hands) to more then double the price of that they were at, in theſe parts, when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had their ſhare in them. Whereby it appeareth how ſincerely this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> ſlighteth this matter as a poore end, though it ſo much enrich the <hi>Dutch</hi> Company; as likewiſe how much, not onely the whole Realme of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> but even all the Kingdomes and Common wealths in <hi>Europe,</hi> that are thus ſerved with thoſe Spices at ſuch high rates, are intereſſed in this cauſe. And yet beſides all the premiſes, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company finde another and more proper cauſe of their recourſe to the preſſe at this preſent, otherwiſe for all the reſt they could perhaps attend other remedies. But they finde that in this Interim, of the cauſe and motives whereof the world could take no notice, many not onely of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> but <hi>Engliſh</hi> alſo, begin to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue worſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> cauſe: preſuming that if it had beene ſuch as the diſcourſes formerly publiſhed in this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument imported, they thinke certainely, ere this, to haue heard of ſome exemplary puniſhment vpon ſo execrable a fact, or at leaſt of ſome ſerious preparation thereunto. In particuler the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company vnderſtand, that ſome of the bloudy Colledge of Iudges, being returned into the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and living free, and well countenanced there, have of late, vpon confidence (as it ſeemes) of the effectuall working of their eluſory Artifice, craked and vaunted, that they will juſtifie their proceſſe of <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> even to the face of his Majeſtie, (which are their owne
<pb facs="tcp:5711:4"/>
facing words) although the ſame parties at their firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ivall in <hi>Holland;</hi> kept themſelues cloſe, and were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owne where to be found, when the Miniſters of this ſtate ſought after them. Which bold face being put vpon this bad matter, hath ſo farre countenanced the ſame, as that ſome of our owne Nation there, allied to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ue in private ſtept vp in defence of the ſayd barbarous butchery, and ſeeme at leaſt to thinke the matter aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above the true deſert, Wherefore leaſt the poore innocent <hi>Engliſh</hi> that haue already ſuffered ſo many and ſo grievous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rtures, and afterwards a reproachfull death, ſhould now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aine after death, ſuffer in their good names alſo, which is, or ought to be, dearer then life it ſelfe, leaſt alſo the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Eaſt India</hi> Company, that haue likewiſe ſuffered too many indignities, and ſuch damages from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> ſhould ſeeme to haue made a great cry without as juſt a cauſe; They now finde it high time to vindicate their owne reputation, and the fame of their innocent ſervants and Country-men, by accquainting the world with the true ſtate of the buſineſſe, as alſo to defend and maintaine their former true relation from the exceptions taken againſt it, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> following Remonſtrance of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> And becauſe the Acts of the proceſſe of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> are often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, as well in this Remonſtrance, as in the Reply therevnto, the ſame alſo are inſerted betweene both, to cleare the relatiue paſſages on both parts. (⸪)</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5711:5"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5711:5"/>
                  <head>A REMONSTRANCE of the Bewinthebbers or Directors of the Netherlands <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company lately exhibited to the Lords States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in iuſtification of the proceedings of their Officers at <hi>Amboyna</hi> againſt the Engliſh there.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Tranſlated out of French.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>High and mighty Lords:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Directors of the vnited Company and Society of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> did in the moneth of Iuly paſt, preſent vnto your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours a Deduction concerning that which was paſt in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and of the execution there made in March 1623, with a proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionall anſwer of the Obiections which then were made and knowne againſt it: But where this Cauſe by that meanes could not be ended, and for as much as daily there are found &amp; ſpred abroad great Bruits againſt that which is mentioned in the Deduction
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5711:6"/>
aforeſaid; therefore the ſaid <hi>Directors</hi> in regard of their charge and office, as alſo for the defence of their Seruants, ſo farre as reaſon permitteth, and not to be thought deſtitute and naked of good defence, yea that they may not leaue the matter for condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as diuers haue ſpred abroad, and gladly would make the world beleeue, cannot forbeare to make, after due reuerence, this more particular Inſtruction in forme of Remonſtrance vnto your Honors.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt place then, the <hi>Directors</hi> doe yet perſiſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> in their ſaid Deduction, becauſe the ſame may ſerue to giue light to the whole cauſe: And conſidering the waighty and infallible Inditia and euidence that preceded this diſcouery of the Treaſon of certaine Engliſh, yea the ſame being notorious, as alſo the proceedings which haue legally and according to Law paſſed againſt the Confederates, as appeareth by the Iudiciall Acts (ſigned as well by thoſe which were examined, as by the Councell of <hi>Amboyna</hi> which is a Colledge admitted and ſworne) and againſt which no proofe, much leſſe any vaine and friuolous ſuſpition ſhould bee admitted, They the <hi>Directors</hi> abſolutely beleeue (ſo long as they ſee no more to the contrary) that the ſaid Engliſh Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators and other Confederates which were in our ſeruice, were well apprehended, and the fact (in our opinions) ſo well proued according to Law, and the vſe &amp; cuſtome in ſuch caſe obſerued, the proceedings haue been leg all, &amp; in purſuir therof the puniſhment which they haue ſuſtained was inflicted according to the common Law, with good moderation of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> the rigour of Iuſtice &amp; with clemency. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5711:6"/>
there haue beene many Writings and Deduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as the <hi>Directors</hi> vntill this time perceiue and diſcouer, ſowed and ſpred againſt this cauſe as well in <hi>England</hi> as in theſe parts: among which (for as much as we know) the firſt is a ſummary of Newes out of Letters dated the 10 of Iune 1623, written by the Engliſh Factors at <hi>Batauia,</hi> which immediately will be iudged by euery one who neuer ſo little and ſuperficially ſhall reade the ſame, to be full of paſſion contrary to the Truth, and without any proofe: For firſt the proceeding by the Iuſtice at <hi>Amboyna</hi> vpon the Confederates there, is blamed therein, and by preiudication called an vniuſt Murder, wicked and barbarous, the faſhion and manner of the racke or torture likewiſe deſcribed and exaggerated with great vehemency and paſſion: And alſo it is not true that therein is ſaid, that the other <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> (beſides the Engliſh) confederates in the fact were Seruants of the Engliſh Company, whereas it appeareth otherwiſe, to wit, that the <hi>Indian</hi> confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates were Seruants of the Dutch Company, as is well knowne to be true; and yet this writing hath taken great place amongſt great and ſmall, and hath beene ſhowed as a patterne or modell whereupon the other griefes haue beene formed againſt the ſaid Iuſtice of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> Vpon which incontinently <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> followed a more large and ample Writing called <hi>The true Relation of the cruell and barbarous torture and execution committed by the Flemings vpon the Engliſh in</hi> Amboyna.</p>
                  <p>In the Introduction whereof proceedeth imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently a deſcription of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and of the Gariſon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5711:7"/>
and force of the Dutch in the ſame place, and this onely to the end, as appeareth, to ſhow thereby that there is no appearance that the Engliſh ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of the taking of the ſaid place as a thing impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; As if, by reaſon of the ſmall vnderſtanding and ſimple foundation which the Conſpirators had to put their deſigne in execution and in effect (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all other accuſations) they had not in any kind merited and deſerued any puniſhment: the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whereof appeareth to be practiſed daily in the like crimes; And to cite this preſumption vnto the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilating <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> of a truth ſo notorious and proued, and againſt the proper confeſſions of the executed and other Confederates, againſt the conſcience and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of ſo many honeſt men and of credit, which haue beene imployed in the cauſe, and againſt a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Iudges publicke and ſworne, this cannot in any manner be admitted, receiued, nor had in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration by ſuch as haue vnderſtanding in theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. But to the contrary and beſides all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> aforegoing, the Dutch Company hath made it to appeare by good proofes, that the Engliſh to the end to diuert and get forth of the Caſtle the forces of the Dutch, had in the Countries and Ilands ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts ſtirred vp, induced, and cauſed to rebell, all the Ternatanes, Ceraniens, and the <hi>Indian</hi> nations bordering there, openly and by publicke violence to make ſuch vnaccuſtomed outrages vpon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the Caſtle, that the Gouernor might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to goe forth from thence with all his forces for to appeaſe and quiet the ſaid Rebells, and to bring them to their ancient obedience. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5711:7"/>
the Engliſh ſhould haue aſſayled and inuaded the Caſtle and the Towne (as being deſtitute by the retiring and departure of the Army) then when the Dutch ſhould be moſt feeble and in their greateſt neceſſity as well of men as of Dutch ſhips, which ſhould haue beene imployed in this voyage. And concerning the force of the Engliſh which were in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> 
                     <hi>Amboyna,</hi> they alone would not haue enterpriſed the attempt, but would vnto this purpoſe haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto them all the ſlaues which they had in great number in their Factaries: Neither would they haue begunne the ſame before the ariuall of certaine Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Ships in <hi>Amboyna:</hi> The people whereof they would alſo haue ſet on worke and imployed to the attempt: The retinue alſo, which daily the compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did vnderhand procure (as <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> Cape Merchant of the Engliſh had ordered) ſhould haue beene much augmented, the rebell ſubiects of the Caſtle ſhould haue weakned the force of the Dutch and augmented the force of the conſpirators; And further (which is the principall point) the end and deſigne of the Conſpirators was not to force and conſtraine the Caſtle (onely) by violence, open warre, or ſiege, (to which purpoſe all theſe imagined fortreſſes of the Caſtle, and the power of the Dutch, might haue their conſideration) but the plot was, to inuade the Caſtle by Treaſon, and with the aid and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> aſſiſtance of the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers which were then in the ſeruice of the Dutch at <hi>Amboyna</hi> aforeſaid: which ſmall number of <hi>Iaponians</hi> were not ſlightly to be regarded, in reſpect of the valour and proweſſe of that Nation, and their extraordinarie reſolution in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5711:8"/>
hazarding their liues in any dangerous enterpriſes; Inſomuch as a certaine ſmall number of the <hi>Iaponi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> onely of themſelues and without any aide or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port haue vndertaken and accompliſhed the moſt great attempts and deſignes in places of the greateſt and moſt puiſſant gouernment in the <hi>Indies.</hi> As a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things it appeareth by that which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the kingdome of <hi>Patany:</hi> where certaine <hi>Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> forced and pillaged the Towne, afterwards made their retreat in good order and with good compoſition. And in the Kingdome of <hi>Siam</hi> in the Towne called <hi>Iodea,</hi> full of thouſands of perſons, the King whereof himſelfe can in a ſhort time bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field aboue one hundred thouſand men of armes, and heretofore obtained great victories vpon many great Princes his neighbours, who then were and as yet are of great power; in that towne (I ſay) which is the capitall Towne of the Kingdome, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Iaponians</hi> ſurprized firſt the Caſtle and Royall Palace, and being entered thereinto by force, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they tooke the King in perſon priſoner, they kept him in their cuſtody, and being wholly become maſters of the ſaid Caſtle, they made by meanes of threatnings (as to put the King to death, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) an honourable and aduantageous compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: By which the ſaid ſmall number of <hi>Iaponians</hi> went away &amp; departed without any domage out of the Kingdome of <hi>Siam,</hi> with great glory and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity, and very great riches. Which exploits are without compariſon much more great and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then the ſaid attempt of <hi>Amboyna</hi> againſt an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Towne and a Caſtle empty and naked of forces,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5711:8"/>
into which alſo the <hi>Iaponians</hi> might haue their daily acceſſe with the Engliſh who were held and reputed for friends: So that whatſoeuer is mentioned in the Deduction of the Engliſh vpon this preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to draw into a doubt all the actions of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, is altogether without foundation, in a Cauſe ſo notorious and publikely conuinced. Of the like <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> force and efficacie is that which is ſet downe before in the ſaid Engliſh Deduction, as if the Dutch had no other deſigne by this imputation of Treaſon but to thruſt forth the Engliſh out of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and to remaine ſole Maſters of the Trade in thoſe quarters: But if ſuch had beene the intention of the Dutch Company, they might eaſier and with more appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and pretext haue forborne to receiue and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Engliſh at the beginning in <hi>Amboyna</hi> in the yeare 1620, then haue thruſt them forth in ſuch a manner: and God forbid that any one ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to performe or effect ſuch a thing by ſuch vniuſt and maligne proceedings, and with ſuch effuſion of blood, onely to thruſt forth the Engliſh from <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna.</hi> And concerning the Dutch Company here <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> in <hi>Europe,</hi> neuer any ſuch thing came into their thoughts, nor did they euer giue any Commiſſion for the putting forth of the Engliſh, by warrant whereof the Officers of the ſaid place in generall might haue had ground to begin any thing to ſuch an end. And concerning the Officers themſelues, they are by thoſe that know them eſteemed and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be honeſt and worthy men: who in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner would no wayes entertaine a thought of ſuch an Action.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5711:9"/>And to ſay the Truth, why ſhould the Officers with ſuch feigned wrong accuſe and put to death the Engliſh and the Confederates being innocent: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that (as aforeſaid) they had no Commiſſion, and if they had any giuen them (which cannot bee well imagined) yet the Gouernor and Counſell of <hi>Amboyna</hi> are ſuch people as would not haue yeelded or giuen obedience thereunto. And the ſame Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour nor other Iudges which are fourteene in number, could not haue drawne any profit or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage by their ſo doing. For admit it were ſo that the Engliſh came in this regard for to leaue <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> this could no wayes aduantage them in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; but to the contrary, returning vnto <hi>Europe,</hi> they themſelues ſhould be (beſides the burthen and remorſe of their owne Conſciences) charged and aggrauated with great blame and infamy, hatred and malice, and put in great danger of their perſons; So that, of ſuch a thing they could not expect other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then detriment, diſaduantage and diſgrace, yea puniſhment and chaſtiſement vpon themſelues. Now if this be not ſo, then may not this preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Engliſh be true, nor in any wiſe admitted and receiued, who maintaine and inhumanely ſay, that this moleſtation and deſtruction was offered and done to the Engliſh, to the end to deliuer and free <hi>Amboyna</hi> of them, and to retaine it onely by the Dutch. For the Dutch Company doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the amity of the Engliſh Company to be vnto them of chiefe and ſpeciall importance; and they deſire for to enioy the ſame with all confidence: And furthermore wee could produce and alleadge
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5711:9"/>
many reaſons why we yet deſire that the treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing religiouſly and piouſly obſerued from the one part to the other, we could willingly and gladly bee content to giue way to the rate and portion in Trade permitted to the Engliſh Company by the Treaty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the yeare 1619. without by excluſion of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh (the Treaty being by them obſerued) to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or thinke of any profit or aduantage in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or in particular.</p>
                  <p>We vndertake further for our officers of <hi>Amboyna</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="K"/> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> alſo it is true) that the beginning and entrance of this proceeding beganne vpon vehement and well grounded ſuſpitions againſt the firſt <hi>Iaponian</hi> in our ſeruice, who walking at vndue houres vpon the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes of the Caſtle, and inquiring very curiouſly of the force and conſtitution of the Gariſon and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the watch, was apprehended, and preſently the clew of this great and execrable conſpiracy was opened and diſcouered, as the Engliſh Deduction it ſelfe confeſſeth.</p>
                  <p>And if the Dutch had deſigned and vndertaken (as moſt calumniouſly it is ſuſpected and reported) to thruſt the Engliſh out of <hi>Amboyna</hi> by the vniuſt report and accuſation of their ſeruants there, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any appearance of any true conſpiracy: why did this <hi>Iaponian</hi> come vpon the walls and ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly enquire, and alſo being apprehended and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined ſo pertinently ſpeake of the conſpiracy? If this <hi>Iaponian</hi> had bin a perſon ſuborned for to charge and accuſe the Engliſh, the Dutch would not haue executed him; which yet legally followed, whereby it appeareth that his declaration and teſtimony was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5711:10"/>
true, as well in accuſing the other <hi>Iaponians</hi> his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes which were in our ſeruice, as in the charge of the other Engliſh, and of himſelfe: why alſo were the other <hi>Iaponians</hi> indicted and executed, if the Dutch ſought it but onely vpon the Engliſh, as is without colour pretended? for the <hi>Iaponians</hi> haue euer been in good eſteeme with vs, and haue alwaies beene much truſted, and not hauing any occaſion of malice, or rancor, or feare of them, or againſt them; where now to the contrary by this tranſgreſſion it behoueth our nation to be alwayes in miſtruſt of the <hi>Iaponians,</hi> and not ſo confidently to vſe or be ſerued of them as before. And it ought not to ſeem ſtrange that during this Examination of theſe <hi>Iaponians</hi> (which as aforeſaid, was begunne and ended before any thing was done to the Engliſh) that the Engliſh for the ſpace of three or foure dayes (although here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> they ſpare the truth) were ſo forward and ſo bold as to goe in and out, to and from the Caſtle: For they thought that it would tend and ſerue vnto their conſeruation, to the end they might giue the leſs ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition: for if they had fled away, &amp; hidden or concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led themſelues; in ſuch caſe they had bin publikely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered. And if they had thought or would haue attempted to flye, it was impoſſible for them ſo to doe, for the Gouernor and Councell had giuen or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all about for the aſſurance of the place, and of all perſons which frequented and had any intercourſe of Merchandizes in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> of which the Engliſh complices could not be ignorant; ſo that they were conſtrained to put on a good face, cheere, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, the better to ſhunne the perill and danger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:5711:10"/>But it further appeareth that that which the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> maintaine is abuſiue and erroneous; that they had continued three or foure dayes in going to and from the Caſtle after the ſaid impriſonment, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the examination of the <hi>Iaponians:</hi> For they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to examine the <hi>Iaponians</hi> the 24 of February, and the 25 the Engliſh were areſted, ſo that there was but one day betweene them both, and therefore that which is mentioned in the Engliſh Deduction is not true. Alſo for the confeſſion of the firſt <hi>Iaponian,</hi> as likewiſe of all the reſt of the <hi>Iaponians</hi> vnto the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of twelue, they do not onely accuſe the Engliſh, but themſelues alſo; ſo that there cannot be any ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition or doubt of falſe accuſation, ſeeing that they themſelues could not haue any aduantage in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of their owne perſons; as otherwiſe there can be no ſuſpition of calumny: which in ſuch a caſe could not be nor happen in any faſhion or manner.</p>
                  <p>That which is contained in the Engliſh Deduction,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> to wit, that the Engliſh had neuer kept any conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with the <hi>Iaponians,</hi> appeareth to the contrary by the Acts of the Proceſſe and the confeſſions of all, and particularly of <hi>Towerſon,</hi> made without Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Fetters, long after his examination. So that from theſe contrarieties and diſſimulations are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, many other ſignes and tokens for to beleeue that the Engliſh Deduction doth wander and ſtray very much from the truth, and that all which may be conſtrued to the contrary is true, in conſequence of that which the Dutch Company of the Eaſt Indies doe ſuſtaine in the iuſt defence of their Officers and Miniſters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5711:11"/>But that whereby the ſaid Deduction is enlarged <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> and amplified, is to make mention and diſcouer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particularities which in time hereafter ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed and proued to be matter meerely fained in the moſt part of the moſt important and ſubſtantiall points: as alſo in that which they ſpeake of the racke and torture giuen to the Engliſh, which is deſcribed in particulars contrary to the truth, thereby to moue the Reader to pitty. But when they haue ſaid all, it is but a bare and naked Diſcourſe without proofe, that the Engliſh haue beene tortured and racked: for to giue the torture when the caſe ſo requireth, is no fault of the Iudge, but it is a thing cuſtomable throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſo in the <hi>Low-countries;</hi> And if ſuch torture hath been giuen to ſome of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, it was ſurely done vpon good and pregnant eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and weighty proofes, and confeſſions of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whereof ſome may haue beene brought to a more rigorous examination, according to the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the caſe, without doing or executing any iniuſtice.</p>
                  <p>If alſo the Iudges of the Dutch would haue wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> preſſed and conſtrained the Engliſh to confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by torture, wherefore did they not preſſe and conſtraine them all to confeſsion: which neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe appeareth by the Deduction of the Engliſh not to haue beene done, and that many were let paſſe without torture; yea many of them which the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Deduction abuſiuely affirmeth to haue beene tortured: it being not reaſonable to proceed againſt them as againſt others which were charged with more great and vehement ſuſpitions and proofes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5711:11"/>And if they proceeded herein with ſuch exceſſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> how commeth it then that the Iudges pardoned and diſcharged ſome (as faulty as the reſt) but onely to giue teſtimony of their proceedings, and that the iuſtice thereof might fully appeare to all whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer? which otherwiſe they were not bound to doe nor would haue done in all likelihood.</p>
                  <p>But to winne the Reader by compaſſion the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> of the torture is there very finely and prolixely ſet downe: but who knoweth not that the manner and faſhion of the extraordinary queſtion is in it ſelfe rough and harſh, and ſpecially muſt ſeeme ſo to the Engliſh in <hi>England</hi> (where there is no ſuch kind of torture vſed, vnleſſe it be in caſe of high Treaſon,) how moderate and gentle ſoeuer it be, as the paine of the torture of the water, which is much more ciuill and leſſe dangerous then other tortures of ſtretching or preſſing, which is in diuers manners vſed in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope:</hi> for ſuch torture and paine of water doth but cauſe and produce an oppreſſion and anxiety of breath, and reſpiration, and not the ſwelling of the body of the Patients (as is abuſiuely mentioned in the Engliſh Deduction) and is without fraction, brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or mutilation of the members which others are ſubiect vnto: So that all which is compriſed and contained in the ſame deſcription is onely ſet downe for the embelliſhing and adorning of the ſaid Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to the end onely to moue the Reader to compaſſion, to make him inſenſibly to draw in and ſwallow all the other errours and vntruths vnder theſe cloſe conueighances, and giue them credit to the aduantage of the drift of the ſaid Deduction:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5711:12"/>
But he which to the contrary will ſound and ſearch out the truth, and whether that which is therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and related bee proued, and ought to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and receiued or not, let him bee pleaſed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to obſerue, as followeth.</p>
                  <p>That all which is ſaid therein is without proofe, and if that any proofe be found therein, it is of very few perſons, yea ſuch as in a cauſe that concerneth themſelues, and wherein they were once iudicially conuinced, may not bee admitted for witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Iudge and the proceedings paſt againſt themſelues, nor againſt the legall confeſſion which they once and oftener made and confirmed with their owne ſubſcription, which now by other depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions or particular declarations, cannot bee made vaine and eluſory againſt the teſtimony and certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of fourteene Iudges, who were preſent in and at all paſſages, whoſe reputation and wiſedome is ſo well knowne, that ſuch wicked, vnorderly and vniuſt proceedings as the Engliſh pretend, may not bee in any ſort or manner charged or imputed vpon them.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, concerning certaine Declarations and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> Writings of the condemned Engliſh before their death, whereby they haue proteſted their innocency, and that they were iudged wrongfully, whereupon by preſumption is inferred that it muſt be true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not to bee beleeued that any one was ſo wicked and impious as to dare to faine and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the houre of his death, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>This Argument maketh little in the cauſe; for firſt it ought to appear that there are indeed ſuch Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Writings of the Engliſh: But the truth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5711:12"/>
can be teſtified by them which were preſent, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them at all times, that there is no ſuch thing; much leſſe that which is ſaid concerning certaine pretended miracles which had happened in witneſſe of the innocency of the executed, ſo that there ſhould haue ſeemed that they had moued heauen and earth to hide and conceale this deteſtible deed: but howſoeuer it be, who would preſume that honeſt men of reputation and wiſedome knowne and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke would haue ſhowne themſelues ſo impious and vnhumane, as wrongfully and innocently to accuſe the perſons executed: and much leſſe it cannot bee preſumed vnto the charge of a Colledge eſtabliſhed and ſworne.</p>
                  <p>And although that which is aforeſaid appeare and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="T"/> be known firſt by the truth of the thing, as it is caried by the Deduction aforegoing, preſented in Iuly paſt vnto your Honours; and that ſecondly it is credible that by this writing here were broke and decided all obiections and difficulties inferred by the Engliſh, as alſo ſome deeds alleadged, which in regard of the Engliſh might be produced and alledged againſt that which is aforeſaid, and againſt the Legality of the proceedes in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> in ſuch manner that more cannot be required in iuſtification of the behauiors of the Dutch Officers: So it is that the <hi>Directors</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding find it neceſſary (although ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) to repeat and make mention here of many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities which much more fully and all at a blow doe ſhow that the reports ſpred and ſworn with ſuch vehemency by the Engliſh againſt the truth doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the one the other, ſo that nothing more can be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5711:13"/>
had nor reſt of ſuſpition, whereby the proceedings and executions at <hi>Amboyna</hi> may bee accuſed, much leſſe condemned, and in conſequence likewiſe, which the great haſte and aſſiduall precipitation vſed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, hath been wholly done in poſte, for to learne and ſhow the world the truth of the diſcouery in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe; as hereafter ſhall appeare more clearly and euidently.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt place then, ſo it is that the Company after the firſt Deduction of Iuly, haue further vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the laſt Ships out of <hi>Battauia</hi> ariued here in September, and that by Certificate or Atteſtation depoſed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Frederick de Houtman,</hi> chiefe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler of the Indies, and ancient Gouernour of the Iſles of <hi>Mulloques;</hi> that it was firmly and vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeued in <hi>Amboyna</hi> thoughout and of euery one, yea by himſelfe as he yet doth beleeue, that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of the ſaid place, and the <hi>Iaponians,</hi> had truly and really conſpired to inuade the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna</hi> at their beſt opportunity; ſo that none ought in any wiſe to doubt hereof.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, for ſtrong proofe of that which is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, the ſaid Gouernor <hi>de Houtman</hi> comming from the <hi>Molucques</hi> to <hi>Hitto</hi> in <hi>Amboyna</hi> in the moneth of April, <hi>anno</hi> 1623, a certaine Engliſhman called <hi>George Sharock,</hi> Aſſiſtant, (which before had beene alſo priſoner, and examined vpon the ſaid conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and by fauour releaſed and pardoned by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour and Councell of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the ſaid <hi>Sharock</hi> was a good while priuy to the ſaid Conſpiracy, and had promiſed his aſſiſtance) kneeling downe vpon his knees and proſtrating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5711:13"/>
before the feet of the ſaid Governour <hi>de Hout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> (who looked for no ſuch matter) declared with great zeale and good affection, that hee was and ſhould bee all his life time bound and obliged vnto the <hi>Dutch</hi> Company, becauſe (as hee then againe confeſſed) that favour had beene done to him, and hee was left vnpuniſhed for the fault and offence which he had committed and perpetrated; and this was ſpoken by the ſaid <hi>George Sharock,</hi> to the ſaid <hi>de Houtman,</hi> about the 20. of April 1623. when he was already abſolved, releaſed, freed, and out of all feare to be any more moleſted, or queſtioned for the ſaid fact and offence committed as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the ſaid Governour <hi>de Houtman</hi> being at <hi>Batavia,</hi> and being preſent when <hi>Iohn Beomont Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Merchant, (who alſo was a confederate in the ſaid conſpiracy at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and obtained his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don) being ſicke, was brought before the Governor generall; and the ſaid <hi>Beomont</hi> being come in the preſence of the ſaid Governor generall, and of the ſaid M. <hi>Houtman,</hi> confeſſed his fault before made and committed, and implored, and moſt humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired mercy and pardon of the ſaid Generall, which having obtained, he humbly thanked them.</p>
                  <p>In the fourth place, That many people at <hi>Batavia,</hi> yea he the <hi>Deponent</hi> himſelfe had by good informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and knowledge, certainely vnderſtood, that the ſaid <hi>Iohn Beomont</hi> being afterwards come before the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſident and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants reſident at <hi>Batavia,</hi> hee the ſaid <hi>Beomont</hi> recited and confeſſed the whole buſineſſe and conſpiracy: But when this pleaſed not the ſaid <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the Preſident of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5711:14"/>
                     <hi>Engliſh</hi> aforeſaid, for to obſcure the cauſe, and to ſhunne the diſhonour of the Treaſon, ſeeing the free confeſſion of <hi>Beomont</hi> which much aſtoniſhed them, he cauſed him for this cauſe to keep cloſe and not to ſpeake to any body, becauſe that the thing by the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary confeſſion of the ſaid <hi>Beomont</hi> againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> principalls, ſhould not further be diſcovered and confirmed.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, concerning the perſons which were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as Iudges in the cauſe of <hi>Amboyna</hi> in the matter of the condemned, and ſpecially the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>Van Speult</hi> (becauſe hee is beſt knowne) they are ſuch, that there cannot be any the leaſt ſuſpition or doubt of them, that they had wrongfully or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſufficient ground cauſed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or ill handled, or much leſſe to bee put to death, if they had not beene found really in fault, worthily to haue deſerved the puniſhment: the Governour <hi>Van Speult</hi> being held for an honeſt man, of credit, and fearing God, by all thoſe that haue converſed with him: and by conſequence, there may not bee admitted ſuch a contrary ſuſpition of his impious and maligne proceedings.</p>
                  <p>In the fift place, concerning the Torture of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which the <hi>Dutch</hi> haue alwayes vſed in the <hi>Indies,</hi> as the moſt aſſured and civill: which is not a torture ſo rough and dangerous as the tortures which are ordinarily vſed in this Country, and throughout <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> which are farre more ſevere and dangerous then that of Water; whereby the health of the perſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not any way be offended, nor the membrs lamed or bruiſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:5711:14"/>All which things aforeſaid, in repreſentation and maintenance of the truth in this caſe, and which fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might be in conformity of what is aforeſaid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by the comming and arriving of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons out of the <hi>Indies,</hi> who alſo haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that which paſſed at <hi>Amboyna:</hi> May it pleaſe your Honors to take into conſideration, and to conſider whether there bee not ſufficient matter and cauſe given to the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt Indian</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for to leaue and remit the fault vnto them, who were the authors and practiſers of this abominable conſpiracy, &amp; of their owne misfortune, which they thus drew vpon themſelues, and not to defend them, and aggravate againſt the Iudges of the <hi>Dutch:</hi> to which end the <hi>Directors</hi> in defence and maintenance of their Officers, and vnblameable Miniſters in the <hi>Eaſt Indies</hi> aforeſaid, cannot omit to beſeech your Honors, that the cauſe may not bee precipitated, but that covenient time might bee given and granted for a more exact reſearch, (if need bee) of the truth, yea in all to grant them ſuch protection, as all good Subjects and Patriots of the Vnited Provinces are to attend from your Honors in equity and juſtice. For now can this buſineſſe be ſo inverted, that in ſtead of the diſhonour and blame which ought to dwel vpon the Confederates, on the contrary now, they will blot and ſmother the truth of the thing, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and charg the <hi>Dutch</hi> Officers, as if they had had no honeſty or conſcience: which cannot bee preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of ſubſtantiall people, of good renowne, vpon any either voluntarie (though not true) or ſuborned and falſe depoſition, of ſuch as may not be admitted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5711:15"/>
to teſtifie in their owne cauſe againſt the judiciall Acts of a Colledge of Iudges, ſworne, and in ſo great a number, which haue of a long time beene ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed; when it appeareth not otherwiſe by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther legall proofes.</p>
                  <p>The intention of the <hi>Directors</hi> never was, nor yet is to maintaine any injuſtice, outrage, or impoſture, if in theſe proceedings there were any vſed: but as long as it appeareth not clearely (as it ought in this caſe, againſt a Colledge, and againſt a cauſe judged) nothing elſe, vnder reverence, can be done in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, but to grant time for to make more exact and ſerious ſearch (if need be,) and that by the authority and intervention of your Honours (as it ſhall apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) all miſ-vnderſtanding, contrary Deductions, and ill expoſitions, griefes, and deſignes, may ceaſe and bee ſurpreſſed, vntill ſuch time as the contrary may (if need bee) appeare. The ſaid Defences are ſuch (in our opinion) as vnder reverence this ought to be done. And although it were ſo, that the cauſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> againſt the Iudges of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wholly to be cleare and proved, (which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath proved to the contrary) nevertheleſſe the proceedings of the ſaid Iudges may not in any wiſe be condemned (as touching the ſubſtance thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) without hearing the Iudges themſelues, whom the cauſe properly toucheth and concerneth, and not the <hi>Directors;</hi> who onely mediate, for as much as according to the information and knowledge which they haue of the cauſe, it ſeemeth to them to be in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect juſt and faire, and therefore the humble remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance or repreſentation and prayer of the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5711:15"/>
or <hi>Directors,</hi> haue ever beene, that it would pleaſe yours Honours to giue and grant covenient time for the inquiry, information, and re-ſearch of the buſineſſe, vntill ſuch time as the ſhips of <hi>Batavia,</hi> ſhall be arrived here; to the end that the matter may more plainly and truely be diſcovered and knowne; and without doubt there will come, and be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therein from thence, ſome that will neutrally and in ſuch ſort maintaine vnto your Honours, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular informations of the proceedings paſſed in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> that they may be wholly beleeved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: as at this preſent there is come, and fallen out by the comming and returne of M. <hi>Fredericke de Houtman,</hi> chiefe Councellor of the <hi>Indies,</hi> and ancient Governour of the Iſles of <hi>Molucques,</hi> who hath depoſed and by oath teſtified the points in manner as they are recited and related in order as aboue, which bringeth not a little light in this cauſe, but may who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tend and turne to the overthrow of all contrary expoſitions and calumnies, which heretofore haue beene vſed and ſet forth, with ſuch differences and vehemency, wherby we hope that your Honors will in all points, and that with equity, right, and reaſon, giue and cauſe to be given ſuch content, that all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content (at leaſt by proviſion) may ceaſe, vntill ſuch time as the whole truth may more and abundantly come to light, by advice from the <hi>Indies,</hi> to the full ſatisfaction of thoſe whom it toucheth or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth. For may it pleaſe your Honors to know and vnderſtand, that the beſt and moſt pertinent and true knowledg of the buſineſſe, muſt come from the Province of <hi>Amboyna</hi> to <hi>Batavia,</hi> and from thence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5711:16"/>
hither. Notwithſtanding, ſo it is, that ſince the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the Pinace called the <hi>Hare</hi> from <hi>Batavia,</hi> which was in the beginning of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1624. (by which the firſt notice of the execution was brought) vntill the departure of the laſt ſhips which alſo came from <hi>Batrvia,</hi> there is not, nor cannot haue come any newes from <hi>Amboyna</hi> to <hi>Batavia,</hi> concerning this buſineſſe, becauſe the winde called the Weſterne Mouſſons blow continually from November vntill Aprill. And for to come from <hi>Amboyna</hi> to <hi>Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> an Eaſterne Mouſſon is neceſſary; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth firſt in May: ſo that without that; it is a thing impoſſible to ſend or get any advice or ſhips from <hi>Amboyna</hi> to <hi>Batavia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We hope alſo that your Lordſhips will finde this reaſonable, and that due and reaſonable time requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhall be granted and permitted in juſtice, for the more ample ſearch and information of the cauſe, (if need be) and we cannot conjecture, (being a thing incredible) that any one will condeme any cauſe or perſons, without firſt hearing the juſtification of the parties, which alwaies hath beene held and obſerved inviolably of all nations, which would judge accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to right and equity. Therefore wee hope that it will be thus granted; yea it is not reaſonable that any reparation ſhould bee required, before the due defences and informations of the buſineſſe bee made and taken, and the ſame ought to be made and taken by and from the perſons whom the cauſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, appertaineth, and is knowne, and who alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently know how to refute the objections and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances alleadged, and heretofore vrged to the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5711:16"/>
contrary: which vnto vs is impoſſible to doe, not having been preſent: but only for the defence of our Officers, for ſo much as is juſt and reaſonable, wee can alleadge that which they haue written vnto vs from the <hi>Indies,</hi> and what elſe we haue certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and vnderſtood.</p>
                  <p>Alſo we cannot in the meane time conceale from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="W"/> your Honours, that the fact of this conſpiracy is ſo notorious in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and that thence may bee drawne ſo ſtrong and vigorous proofes, that the Truth ſhall fully and ſufficiently appeare to the full diſcharge of the innocents, and the confuſion of thoſe which will defend and maintaine a bad cauſe; And this may bee proved there beſides the points aboue alleadged.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that all the <hi>Iaponians,</hi> complices in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy haue ſigned each with their own hands their confeſſions, and afterwards jointly and all altogehet haue perſiſted therein after the end of the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without torture or fetters, at many ſittings and full aſſemblies of the Councell at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out revoking any thing, or deſiring to diminiſh or augment any thing from or to their ſaid confeſſions.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond place, That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Complices at ſundry times of their own accord, without paine, irons, tortures, or menaces, ratified the ſame, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiuely ſigned their confeſſions: vpon which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, they were afterwards againe examined three or foure times, and re-examined in a full Councell and Aſſembly; and after their examination haue perſiſted therein, without revoking or changing any thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:5711:17"/>Thirdly, that the Governour of <hi>Amboyna</hi> (after that all the complices had reſpectiuely foure or fiue times ratified their confeſſions, and perſiſted therein a little before the execution, ſeriouſly remonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, exhorted, repreſented, and demanded, of the ſaid complices (as before had done vnto them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular) That in caſe any one of them had by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of juſtice, feare of menaces, or terrour of paine, ſaid, confeſſed, and ſigned any thing, by which he was ſurprized and made guilty, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by others might come and fall into danger or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, that hee ſhould ſpeake and manifeſt it openly, that he might diſcharge the party thereof. For the Governour proteſted that he was not deſirous of the deſtruction and death of any that was not guilty. Vpon which propoſition every one of them ſhrunke vp their ſhoulders and ſaid, that what he had confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſigned particularly was true, and therefore he perſiſted therein.</p>
                  <p>In the fourth place, One of the complices called <hi>William Webber,</hi> in his laſt examination confeſſed, that he had receiued a Letter from <hi>Iohn Clarke,</hi> by which he was advertiſed, that ſomething of great waight and conſequence was handled amongſt the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> hut he could not vnderſtand what it might be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the which letter containing as aforeſaid, the ſaid <hi>Clarke</hi> confeſſed alſo in the abſcence of <hi>Webber,</hi> that he had written it.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, that <hi>Edward Collins</hi> being examined, and making his confeſſion without any torment or tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (as appeareth by the Acts) offered to confeſſe all of his owne freewill: yea hee declared the ſame
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5711:17"/>
before <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> and all the other Engliſh, and that he did not thinke that the ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> and all the reſt which were there faulty would dare to deny it, but would preſently confeſſe it, as alſo the ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> being brought to <hi>Collins</hi> (and the ſaid <hi>Collins</hi> falling vpon his knees and requiring mercie and pardon) he ſaid, and told it him to his face, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing the ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> that he would preſently declare and confeſſe all as he had done, ſaying, I muſt ſpeake and confeſſe the truth, and I meane not to ſuffer or endure any paine for the loue of you.</p>
                  <p>In the ſixt place, That <hi>Emanuel Tompſon</hi> two dayes after the examination finiſhed and ended, and when he was free and at liberty, being inquired by the Commiſſioners which had aſſiſted in the ſame examination, wherefore he had ſo long perſiſted in his denials and endured the ſeuere examination, ſaid, the reaſon was becauſe Captaine <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> had oftentimes reprehended his drunkenneſſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that hee ſhould take good heed that thereby the matter ſhould not be diſcouered; For which cauſe he ſaid <hi>Tompſon</hi> did by a great oath ſweare to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that howſoeuer it went hee would not bee the third nor the fourth by whom the matter ſhould be knowne, whatſoeuer paine (in his opinion) he could haue beene put vnto.</p>
                  <p>Seuenthly, the ſaid <hi>Emanuel Tompſon</hi> certaine daies after his examination being viſited by certaine Commiſſioners ſaid vnto them that hee was very glad that God had cauſed the buſineſs to be brought to light, becauſe much innocent blood would haue beene ſpilt, and although he confeſſed that hee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5711:18"/>
had deſerued once, yea twice to dye, he asked mercy ſeeing that he was a man of about fiftie yeares, &amp;c. And ſo after ſo much fauour was giuen to the ſaid <hi>Tompſon</hi> for to draw a lot with <hi>Coulſon</hi> and <hi>Collins</hi> which of them three ſhould be releaſed and freed.</p>
                  <p>In the eight place, that two or three dayes before the execution, Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> being in the Hall with other the conuict Engliſh, ſaid in the preſence of the Gouernour and all the Councell, and to the reſt of the Engliſh in generall by reproach, that their ill and diſordinate liues, their whoredome and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe was the cauſe that it pleaſed God that they ſhould not keepe ſecret the intended enterpriſe; and that by reaſon thereof they were now fallen and brought to ſuch miſery.</p>
                  <p>Ninthly, that <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> author of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, in his laſt extremitie prayed the reſt of his complices to pardon him, becauſe that by him <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werſon</hi> they were inſtigated and brought vnto the ſaid enterpriſe, and were reduced to that caſe, and that the buſineſſe was come to be diſcouered by the all ſeeing God, and that he muſt of neceſſity dye, and therefore hauing brought them into this danger and ill chance he prayed them to pardon him, as they alſo did.</p>
                  <p>In the tenth place, The ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death writ a Letter to <hi>Samuel Coulſon,</hi> which letter is yet in the hands of the Gouernor of <hi>Amboyna Herman van Speult,</hi> by which the ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> ſaid and alleadged vnto the ſaid <hi>Coulſon,</hi> that he the ſaid <hi>Coulſon</hi> was the firſt and principall cauſe which had made the agreement and condeſcending vnto the act
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5711:18"/>
of inuading and making of themſelues maſters of the Caſtle, but notwithſtanding at the preſent he pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him.</p>
                  <p>Eleuenthly, that the ſhip called the <hi>Vnicorne</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Amboyna</hi> to <hi>Batauia,</hi> the two Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants <hi>Edward Collins</hi> and <hi>Iohn Beomont</hi> which were pardoned were tranſported therein, vnto the end to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>npetrate and obtaine their full pardon in <hi>Batauia</hi> aforeſaid, and they two Engliſh Merchants being requeſted by the officers of the ſhip to come ſit down and eate at the Table of the Commiſſioners, during the ſaid voyage; the ſaid <hi>Collins</hi> ſaid, excuſing of himſelfe, that they were not worthy to ſit by the ſaid Commiſſioners, becauſe that the ſaid Engliſh had had ſuch an ill purpoſe and deſign againſt the Dutch, and yet they were by them in that faſhion entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and were exempted of the puniſhment: and therefore they could very well eate apart: which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe notwithſtanding was not receiued nor accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Commiſſioners of the Dutch.</p>
                  <p>In the twelfth place are adioyned and annexed the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> report and depoſitions of the ſaid Gouernour <hi>de Houtman</hi> concerning the confeſſions of the ſaid two Engliſh Merchants made before the Gouernor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and afterwards before the Preſident and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Engliſh, and that which further may be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at <hi>Batauia,</hi> whereof diuers perſons there haue notice.</p>
                  <p>In the thirteenth place, concerning the torture in the proceedings vſed at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> they can giue certaine proofe of the truth it ſelfe, that many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons mentioned in the Engliſh Writing to haue bin
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5711:19"/>
tortured with water and fire, haue not one beene once touched.</p>
                  <p>In the fourteenth place, concerning the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities and petty points of the ſaid Writing in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh touching the examination of certaine perſons therein mentioned for the diſcharge and innocency of the Engliſh, the ſame ſhall bee proued neuer to haue beene done nor heard, by depoſitions of thoſe which haue beene preſent at all, and by perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom ſuch things muſt needs haue beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and declared.</p>
                  <p>In the fifteenth place, it ſhall alſo bee found that the pretended miracles were deuiſed onely for the diſcharge of the Engliſh, and in their fauour.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſaid points and many others which are yet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Y"/> further well knowne to the <hi>Directors,</hi> may be clearly and by good proofe ſhowne in time and place, if due and conuenient time be giuen and granted vnto the cauſe and re-ſearch thereof: which in a matter ſo important and of ſuch waight, comming alſo from ſo remote parts, cannot (vnder reuerence) be denied to any: So that your Honours may pleaſe to deſire the ſame of his Maieſty of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> without which the <hi>Directors</hi> can very ill propoſe any other meanes which would not be mingled either with iniuſtice, or the great preiudice and diſaduantage of the Dutch Company.</p>
                  <p>We alſo ſurely hope that his ſaid Maieſty accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his great wiſedome and iuſtice cannot refuſe or deny the ſaid reſpite for the examination of the buſineſſe more exactly and particularly; which wee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5711:19"/>
beſeech your Honours in all reuerence to interpoſe and mediate, and by all meanes to effect and obtaine; that (as reaſon requireth) neither the Company in generall, nor the Maſters in particular may not du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this interim be any way grieued or preiudiced in their iuſt defences. Which doing, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5711:20"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5711:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>AN AVTHENTICK COPY OF THE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FESSIONS AND SENTENCES, <hi>AGAINST</hi> M. TOVVERSON, AND COMPLICES, CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING THE BLOVDY CONSPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy enterpriſed againſt the Caſtle of AMBOYNA.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The which by the manifeſt grace and providence of</hi> God, was diſcovered the 23. day of <hi>February,</hi> in the yeare 1623.</p>
                  <p>As alſo the Reſolutions of the Governour <hi>Van Speult,</hi> and of the Councell taken in this buſineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Tranſlated out of their owne Copy.</p>
                  <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN DAVVSON, for the EAST INDIA COMPANY 1632.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="confessions">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5711:21"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5711:21"/>
                  <head>AN AVTHENTICK Copy of the Confeſsions and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences againſt Mr. <hi>Towerſon,</hi> and Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, concerning the bloudy conſpiracy enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed againſt the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> the which by the manifeſt grace, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God was diſcouered the 23. day of <hi>February,</hi> in the yeare 1623. as alſo the Reſolutions of the Governour <hi>Van Speult,</hi> and of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell taken in the buſines.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Tranſlation.</head>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas on the 23. of <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 1623. by the manifeſt grace and providence of God, it was diſcovered; That a certaine <hi>Iaponeſſe</hi> called <hi>Hytieſo,</hi> at night, and at vnlawfull howers at Sermon, and Prayers time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contrary to order, and to his condition, did paſſe divers times along by the Ramparts, and before the Points: and at diuers times there where he found the Souldiers yong and vnexperienced, made enquiry how many Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the <hi>Lowe Countries</hi> there were in the Caſtle,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5711:22"/>
and how many times they changed the watch eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night: The Worſhipfull <hi>Harman van Speult,</hi> Councellor of the <hi>Indies,</hi> and Governour of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> vpon great reaſons taking his actions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for ſuſpicious, cauſed the ſayd <hi>Iaponeze</hi> to appeare before him and the Councell, and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him of the truth, he confeſſed as followeth, <hi>Datum vt ſupra:</hi> Being ſigned</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Harman van Speult, Laurence de Marſchalck, Clement Kerſſeboom, Iohn Iohnſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viſcher, Iohn van Leeuwen, Iohn Iacobſon-wincoop, Leonard Clocq, Martin Ianſon Vogell, Iohn Iooſten, Iacob Cooper, Iohn van Nieupoort, Peter Ianſon van Zanten, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Crayevanger, Rowland Tailler, Vincent Cort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hytieſo Iaponois</hi> of the age of 24. yeares, borne at <hi>Fernado</hi> in <hi>Iapon</hi> denyed the ſame, but the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers being produced before him, of whom he had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times, and in divers places asked thoſe queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he confeſſed that he had done it out of a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſpoſition and for pleaſure: whereupon his Worſh: ſayd vnto him, that ſuch things at vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable times could not be asked for pleaſure of the yonger and vnexperienced Souldiers, but that of neceſſity it muſt be otherwiſe: and in purſuit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being of that opinion, he with thoſe of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, cauſed him to be brought to the torture: the Priſoner having beene tortured a while, deſired that they would ceaſe, and hee would confeſſe all that did belong to the buſines, and then he confeſſed that a certaine other <hi>Iaponeze,</hi> being alſo Souldier to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5711:22"/>
the Dutch Companie in the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> called <hi>Sid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Migiell,</hi> (who had heretofore beene ſervant to the honorable Engliſh Company) had deſired him to enquire of the thing aforeſayd, and moreover he confeſſed, that he had beene asked by the ſayd <hi>Migiell,</hi> if he would lend his ayde amongſt other <hi>Iaponezers,</hi> ro deliver the Caſtle into the hands of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to the which he anſwered, he would vpon condition of good recompence, which was offered him by the ſayd <hi>Iaponeze,</hi> in the name of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hee confeſſed, that hee had communicated and conſulted concerning the delivery of the Caſtle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times, as well in the quarters of <hi>Mardiques,</hi> as in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> houſe with divers other <hi>Iaponezes,</hi> and with Mr. <hi>Timothie Iohnſon</hi> Engliſh Merchant, and <hi>Abell Price</hi> Engliſh Barber, and that within three moneths laſt paſt.</p>
                     <p>He ſayth that the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers which were in the Caſtle, did agree to deliver the ſaid Caſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and that they had inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelues to ſerue them.</p>
                     <p>Further he confeſſeth, that they would put this exploit and treaſon in execution, when any <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhip ſhould haue ariued in this place.</p>
                     <p>Hee ſaith, that the <hi>Iaponezes</hi> did conſult for to keepe two men in every Corner of the Caſtle, and the reſt in the Hall, for to ſeize vpon the Governor, and that they would haue killed all that were not on their ſide:</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Thus confeſſed <date>the 23. of <hi>February</hi> 1623.</date> in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and it was ſubſcribed,</dateline>
                        <signed>the marke of <hi>Hytieſo Iaponois.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:5711:23"/>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Vischer,</item>
                              <item>Iohn van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogel,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="proceedings">
                     <p>By reaſon of which conſpiracie and treaſon, the Governour <hi>Van Speult</hi> being moved and troubled, kept the Priſoner by him, and preſently cauſed the Gate to ſhut and looked to, and the points of the Caſtle with double guard, and likewiſe the Armes of all the <hi>Iaponezes</hi> to be taken away, and themſelues to bee put in Irons: giving commaund that none ſhould ſtirre out of the Caſtle, vntill ſuch time as he ſhould bee better informed, and all things were ſet in order: knowing well that there was great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in delayes, and that for the finding out of ſuch conſpiracies and offences, he was not to make any pauſe, but to ſearch out the end thereof; for which cauſe hee commaunded <hi>Sidney Migiell</hi> to bee ſent for, &amp; commaunded the Advocate <hi>Fiſcall de Brune,</hi> with the Councell, to take diligent information:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5711:23"/>
who after ſome torture, the ſaid <hi>Migiell</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers made the confeſſions following.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Done</hi> in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna</hi> 
                           <date>the 23. of <hi>Feb. Anno</hi> 1623.</date>
                        </dateline> 
                        <signed> And it was ſubſcribed;
<list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sidney Migiell Iaponeze,</hi> of the age of 24. yeares, borne at <hi>Nangaſaque,</hi> confeſſeth that he did enquire of another Souldier being a <hi>Iaponeze,</hi> called <hi>Peter Conge,</hi> how many <hi>Dutch</hi> Souldiers were in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle.</p>
                     <p>He confeſſeth, that <hi>Abell Price</hi> Engliſh Barber within 2. or 3. moneths ſince asked him, if he knew a way for to get and induce the <hi>Iaponezes</hi> to deliver the Caſtle to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He ſaith, that afterwards he conſulted with the <hi>Iaponezes</hi> about the ſaid buſineſſe, and that all of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5711:24"/>
them agreed therevnto.</p>
                     <p>He ſaith, that divers times he conſulted concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the proſecution of the buſineſſe, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the time with Captaine <hi>Towerſon,</hi> M. <hi>Tompſon, Iohn Clarke, Abell Price,</hi> and other <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He confeſſeth alſo, that they would haue put in execution this plot or treaſon, when any <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhip or Pincke had arrived here, and that then with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and their ſlaves, they would haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make themſelues Maſters of the Caſtle, and haue killed all that were not on their ſide.</p>
                     <p>He ſaith, that they had appointed two <hi>Iaponezes</hi> to be in every point of the Caſtle, and the reſt in the Hall, for to ſeize vpon the Governour <hi>Van Speult.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He confeſſeth alſo, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did promiſe to every <hi>Iaponeze</hi> 1000. Ryals of Eight, over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue their ſhare in the bootie. Thus confeſſed the 24. of <hi>February, Anno 1623. Stilo Nouo,</hi> in the Fort of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> And it was ſubſcribed.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>This is the marke of <hi>Sidney Migiell.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>
                                 <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5711:24"/>Peter Ianſen Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Peter Congi Iaponeze,</hi> aged 31. yeares, borne at <hi>Mangaſaque:</hi> confeſſeth, that the ſaid <hi>Migiell</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned him concerning the Souldiers of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> how many there were, and that he enquired of the ſaid <hi>Hytieſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He confeſſeth, that he did conſult as the other <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponezes</hi> did with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> concerning the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Caſtle, and he promiſed his ſervice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Thus confeſſed <date>the 24. of <hi>February</hi> 1623.</date> in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                        </dateline> 
                        <signed> The marke of <hi>Peter Congi.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Tanſen Van Zantem,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5711:25"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Soyſimo, Iaponeze</hi> of the age of 26. yeares, borne at <hi>Ferando:</hi> confeſſeth, that he had likewiſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the conſultation of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and that he had preſented his ſervice to the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> to win the Caſtle. Confeſſed, <hi>Dated</hi> in the ſame place, and it was marked, ſigned, <hi>Soyſimo Iaponeze.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thome Corea Iaponeze,</hi> of the age of 50. yeares, borne at <hi>Mangaſaque:</hi> confeſſed, that hee with the reſt of the <hi>Iaponezes,</hi> had knowledge of the conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and that hee ſhould likewiſe haue beene imployed in their ſervice. Thus confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the 24. of <hi>February</hi> 1623. and was ſigned. </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>The marke of <hi>Thome Corea.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <pb n="9" facs="tcp:5711:25"/>
                              <item>Harman van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Vischer,</item>
                              <item>Iohn van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogel,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tſioſa Iaponeze</hi> of the age of 32. yeares, borne at <hi>Firando</hi> Souldier: confeſſeth, that hee with the reſt of the <hi>Iaponezes</hi> ſhould haue been aſſiſtant in the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing of the Caſtle for the <hi>Engliſh. Datum ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra:</hi> and was ſigned.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>The marke of <hi>Tſioſa Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neze.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iobnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>
                                 <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5711:26"/>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quiendayo Iaponeze,</hi> aged 32. yeares, Souldier, borne at <hi>Coreats:</hi> confeſſed, that they being 12. <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponezes,</hi> thought to haue made themſelues Maſters of the Caſtle with the ayde of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſigned as aforeſaid.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Signed thus the name of <hi>Quiendayo.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell.</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſon Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sinſa Iaponeze,</hi> of the age of 32. yeares, borne at <hi>Ferando,</hi> Souldier: confeſſed, that they 12. <hi>Iaponezes</hi> did intend to deliver and betray the Caſtle to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5711:26"/>
                        <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Confeſſed in the ſaid place, and on the ſaid day ſubſcribed.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>The name of <hi>Sinſa Iaponeze.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck;</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leenwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tſauinda Iaponeze,</hi> aged 32. yeares, borne at <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oucketge,</hi> Souldier: confeſſeth as the reſt, that they 12. with the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> intended to make themſelues Maiſters of the Caſtle. Thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the 24. of <hi>February</hi> 1623. </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>And was ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. The name of <hi>Tſauinda.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>
                                 <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5711:27"/>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Ianſen Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zanchoo Iaponeze,</hi> aged 22. yeares, borne at <hi>Fiſien,</hi> Souldier: Confeſſeth as the afore-going. Dated as the afore-ſaid, and was vnder-ſigned.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>The marke of <hi>Zanchoo.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacokſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5711:27"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sacoube Iaponeze,</hi> of the age of 40. yeares, borne at <hi>Ferando,</hi> Souldier: Confeſſeth, that he alſo had knowledge of the conſultation of the <hi>Iaponezes,</hi> but being old and ſicke, he did not preſent his ſervice. Dated the 25. of <hi>February</hi> 1623. </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>The marke of <hi>Sacoube.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſon Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="proceedings">
                     <p>His Worſhip vnderſtanding by all the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Confeſſions the deſigne of the Agent of the honourable <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> with the Merchants and other Confederates; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that he was ſufficiently informed: that hee might haue taken them into cuſtody, yet he would not haſt thereunto: but firſt he cauſed to be brought before him <hi>Abell Price</hi> Engliſh Barber, who for other offences (as an Incendiarie, for vſing violence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5711:28"/>
in other mens houſes) was already in priſon: and after the ſaid Priſoner was told the place, perſons, and times where he had conſulted with the <hi>Iapone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes,</hi> and with other <hi>Engliſh</hi> vpon the conſultation afore-ſaid: they vnderſtood by him that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. <hi>Dated</hi> the 25. of <hi>February</hi> 1623. Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <p>The Confeſſion of <hi>Abell Price,</hi> aged 24. yeares, borne at <hi>Neles</hi> in <hi>Wales</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Pembroke.</hi> Confeſſed;</p>
                     <p>That he by the command and order of Captaine <hi>Towerſan,</hi> had conference with <hi>Sidney Migiell Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neze,</hi> concerning the taking of the Caſtle, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto every <hi>Iaponeze</hi> their ſhare in the bootie.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:5711:28"/>Further he confeſſeth, that he did treate two or three times in the Quarter of <hi>Mardriques</hi> with M. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> M. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Clarke,</hi> and the <hi>Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezes</hi> concerning the ſaid matter.</p>
                     <p>Further he confeſſeth; That the ſaid <hi>Migiell Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poneze</hi> was three or foure times in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> houſe with him, and conferred with him and them divers times, and they informed Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> of their diſcourſe.</p>
                     <p>Confeſſing further, That the ſaid treaſon ſhould haue been put in execution when any <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhips ſhould arriue.</p>
                     <p>Further he confeſſeth, that all the Merchants of the Facturies, reſorting to <hi>Amboyna,</hi> had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſaid treaſon.</p>
                     <p>Further he ſaith, That they intended to put it in execution when one of their ſhippes ſhould come.</p>
                     <p>Further he confeſſeth, That if they had taken the Caſtle, they would haue done all the dammage and offence poſſible to the Citizens, if they agreed not with them. And this he confirmed with his name <hi>Abell Price.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Worſhip vnderſtanding this, hee thought good for to ſend for Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, the which he did preſently by a certaine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, who went to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Houſe, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly returned to the Caſtle with M. <hi>Towerſon:</hi> who was very much troubled and altered, and then his Worſhip ſaid to him, that hee was very much ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and ſorry for that which he had vnderſtood by the <hi>Iaponeze</hi> and the <hi>Barber;</hi> having many times ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5711:29"/>
the ſaid Captain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> that he ſhould not entertaine or draw vnto him (as hee did) the <hi>Engliſh, Iaponeze,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Priſoners, which were in the ſervice of him and the <hi>Low Countries.</hi> That it did cauſe and giue ſuſpition of ill conſultation, and other things, but as he thought Captaine <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werſon</hi> did not know any thing: but that now hee marked in him a great alteration and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>The Governour <hi>Van Speult</hi> with his Counſell found good that they ſhould retaine by way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion the ſaid Captaine <hi>Towerſon,</hi> and M <hi>Thomſon;</hi> and he was told preſently that he ſhould ſtay there as Priſoner, and ſhould take a lodging in one of the Chambers of the Merchants. But the ſaid Maſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> deſired that by reaſon of his qualitie, they would grant him to be Priſoner in his owne Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in the Houſe of the honourable <hi>Engliſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie: to the which his Worſhip agreed, vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that firſt he ſhould cauſe to come, or ſend all his men into the Caſtle, the which was done; and that he ſhould bee there Priſoner with ſome Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
                     <p>Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> being gone, his Worſhip hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a Counſell thought good preſently to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> one after another, and they were examined; ſome before torture, others after a little torture confeſſing as followeth; Done the 26. of <hi>February</hi> 1623. Signed.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>
                                 <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5711:29"/>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſon Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Timothy Iohnſon</hi> Factor, borne at <hi>New-Caſtle;</hi> aged 29. yeares.</head>
                     <p>Confeſſeth; That he was in one of the houſes of the <hi>Iaponezes,</hi> in the Quarter of the <hi>Madriques</hi> with M. <hi>Thomſon, Iohn Clarke,</hi> and <hi>Abell Price,</hi> three or foure times, for to conſult of the taking of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and of maſſacring thoſe of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> which conſultation, was kept ſix or ſeaven dayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe.</p>
                     <p>Further he confeſſeth; That Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> on New-yeares-day laſt, having all his Merchants aſſembled with him, propoſed vnto them how that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did great injuries to the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> and asked them if they had not the courage to helpe to revenge all their wrongs: for his own part, he knew the wayes and meanes, both within and without,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5711:30"/>
with the ayde of certaine Souldiers <hi>Iaponezes,</hi> that were lodged in the Caſtle, to make himſelfe Maſter thereof. And they all anſwered that they had.</p>
                     <p>And hee confeſſeth; That their exploit ſhould haue beene put in execution, when the Governour ſhould be out of the Caſtle vpon ſome exploit, and thoſe that were in the Caſtle ſhould be weake and ill provided.</p>
                     <p>And alſo that all the Merchants of other Factu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries reſorting thither, had knowledge of the ſaid Treaſon.</p>
                     <p>And further he ſaith; That they would haue ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the bootie with the <hi>Iaponezes,</hi> and this is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the ſigne and name of <hi>Timothy Ianſon,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Robert Browne,</hi> borne in <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burrow</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> aged 24. yeares.</head>
                     <p>Confeſſed; That Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> about <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeares day</hi> laſt paſt, called an Aſſembly of all his Familie and the forraine Merchants, and told them that hee would haue them take an oath on the Bible for fidelitie and ſecreſie, the which they did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
                     <p>Further he ſaith; That afterwards the ſaid <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> propounded, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had ſuffered great wrong by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> asking them if they had the will and courage to revenge the ſame. To the which ſome of them anſwered, that they were to weake to effect it. But then the ſaid Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that they would waite the opportunitie of the arrivall of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships: wherevpon all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5711:30"/>
of them agreed to make tryal, to make themſelues Maſters of the <hi>Caſtle.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Alſo; That <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> reported that the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers that were within the Caſtle were at his ſervice.</p>
                     <p>Saith moreover; That <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> at the arrivall of ſome of their Ships, ſhould cauſe all their Merchants and ſlaves of the other Facturie to come thither for that purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>And further he ſaith; That they would haue kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all that ſhould haue made any reſiſtance againſt them. And it is ſubſcribed by the marke <hi>R. B.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Iohn Fardo</hi> the Engliſh Steward of the age of 42. yeares.</head>
                     <p>He confeſſeth; That about two moneths ſince he was in conference with others, wherein he tooke his oath vpon the Bible to be faithfull and ſecret.</p>
                     <p>He ſaith; That <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> with their ayde, intended to make himſelfe Maſter of the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>And further he ſaith; That ſome whereof hee Priſoner was one, anſwered that they were to weake in men: and <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> ſaid, that he knew a way to finde men enough, and that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the buſineſſe to him, and that they only ſhould doe their endevour.</p>
                     <p>Further he ſaith; That hee amongſt the reſt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſervice and endevour.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore hee ſaith; That about 14. dayes ſince, when he was with <hi>Captaine Towerſon,</hi> for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the Kitchin, <hi>Captain Towerſon</hi> asked him the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5711:31"/>
ſame, and if hee would doe his beſt for to take the Caſtle, to the which hee anſwered, that he among others would doe their beſt. And it was confirmed by the ſigne of <hi>Iohn Fardo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Edward Collins</hi> Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, borne at <hi>London,</hi> aged 25. yeares or ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts.</head>
                     <p>Confeſſeth, That he amongſt others was at the ſaid conſultation, and tooke his oath vpon the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to be faithfull and ſecret.</p>
                     <p>And further; That he amongſt others did conſent to doe his beſt in the taking of the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> That within three or foure dayes after the ſaid conſultation, they aſſembled againe: and then <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> told him, that he had at his devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers, and that at his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they would make themſelues Maſters of the Points, and that ſome ſhould attend in the Hall for the Governour, when he ſhould come forth vpon the noyſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item;</hi> That they would put their deſigne in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when one of their Ships ſhould arriue.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he confeſſeth, That if ſo be they could haue gained the Caſtle, they would haue done the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens all the hurt and dammage poſſible, vnleſſe they would agree with them. And it is confirmed vnder <hi>Edward Collins</hi> his hand.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Iohn Beomont</hi> Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, borne in <hi>Barke-ſhire,</hi> aged 48. yeares.</head>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5711:31"/>Confeſſeth, That on <hi>New-yeares-day</hi> laſt paſt, he was in conference, and among others tooke his oath vpon the Bible to be faithfull and ſecret.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> hee confeſſeth; That <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired all their aydes for the taking of the Caſtle. Other circumſtances at preſent he remembreth not, having beene ſicke, and having an ill memory, and growing in age. And it is confirmed vnder the hand of <hi>Iohn Beomont.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Ephraim Ramſy,</hi> borne at <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſtow</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> aged 21. yeares. Aſsistant to the Engliſh at <hi>Lohoe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He confeſſeth, That vpon <hi>New-yeares-day</hi> laſt, he was at <hi>Lohoe,</hi> and therefore he could not bee at the ſaid conference with the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Further he ſaith; That this is the firſt day that he hath vnderſtood, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did conſult on New-years day for the taking of the <hi>Caſtle</hi> in a time convenient.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Iohn Sadler,</hi> borne at <hi>London,</hi> aged 20. yeares, Engliſh Steward at <hi>Larico.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He confeſſeth, That at the time aforeſaid hee was at <hi>Larico,</hi> and that hee knew not of any conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>William Grigs</hi> of <hi>Dunſtable</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Bedford,</hi> aged 28. yeares, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Merchant at <hi>Larico.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5711:32"/>He confeſſeth; that he was preſent at the conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation vpon New-yeares day laſt, and that amongſt others he took his oath vpon the Bible to be loyall and ſecret</p>
                     <p>Further he confeſſeth, that he offered his ſervice for to take the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item, Captaine Towerſon</hi> did make great complaint of the wrong which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did receiue from the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> and for the revenge thereof with the ayde of the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers, ſlaves, and ſome <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Priſoners, hee intended to make himſelfe Maſter of the Caſtle: if every one of vs would ayde him, the which if we would doe, he knew a way to keepe the Caſtle in ſpight of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> teethes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> hee ſaith, that they would haue killed all thoſe which ſhould make any reſiſtance, and taken the reſt priſoners.</p>
                     <p>Further hee ſaith, that within a few dayes after they ſhould haue had another conſultation, and that then <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> would giue order for all things, and haue given a ſigne to the <hi>Iaponezes,</hi> at which they ſhould haue gone about the buſineſſe within the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he ſaith, that they would haue divided the goods and bootie among themſelues: And it was confirmed vnder the hand of <hi>William Grigs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Iohn Clarke,</hi> borne at <hi>Ordington,</hi> aged 36. yeares. Aſsistant to the Engliſh.</head>
                     <p>Confeſſeth, That he treated and ſpake with the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers concerning the taking of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5711:32"/>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he confeſſeth, That he was in the conſultation on New-yeares day laſt paſt, and that <hi>Captaine To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werſon</hi> cauſed them to take an oath vpon the Bible to be faithfull and ſecret: ſaying that it was neceſſary ſo to doe, for if that which he ſhould ſay vnto them ſhould come to be known, it would coſt them all their liues.</p>
                     <p>Confeſſeth moreover, That Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> ſaid afterwards, that he intended with the helpe of the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers, and them, to make himſelfe Maſter of the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he ſaith, That Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> ſaid, that when time ſhould be fitting, he would ſend for all his men and ſlaves of the other Factories.</p>
                     <p>He ſaith moreover, That they reſolved to kill all thoſe that ſhould reſiſt them, and that they ſhould haue ſhared all the monies &amp; goods amongſt them. And this was confirmed vnder the hand of <hi>Iohn Clarke.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>William Webber,</hi> borne at <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> aged about 32. yeares.</head>
                     <p>He confeſſeth, that about fiue weekes ſince, hee received a Letter from <hi>Iohn Clarke</hi> of <hi>Hitto,</hi> wherein among other things it was written, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Amboyna</hi> had conſulted concerning the taking of the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he ſaith, that he hath no other knowledge of the treaſon, nor he did not conſult with any perſon concerning the ſame. And it was confirmed vnder the hand of <hi>William Webber.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:5711:33"/>
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>George Shacock,</hi> of the age of 31. yeares, borne at <hi>Weſtcheſter,</hi> Aſsistant to the Engliſh at <hi>Hitto.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He confeſſeth and ſaith; That he was not in <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna</hi> ſince the 1. of December laſt paſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee could not be at the conſultation held here by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at New-yeares tide laſt.</p>
                     <p>He confeſſeth, that about a moneth or fiue weeks ſince he vnderſtood of <hi>Iohn Clarke</hi> of <hi>Hitto,</hi> being in the <hi>Gallery</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Amboyna</hi> had conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and reſolved for to take the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> that hee promiſed to <hi>Iohn Clarke</hi> his ayde concerning the buſineſſe. And it was confirmed vnder the hand of the ſaid <hi>George Shacocke.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Samuell Coulſon</hi> Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, borne at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> aged 39. yeares.</head>
                     <p>Confeſſeth; That hee was at the conference of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and had taken an oath vpon the Bible for to be faithfull and ſecret, as others.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he confeſſeth, that Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the great wrong &amp; injuries that the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> did them, and if that they would ayde them he knew with the helpe of the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers, a way to take the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he confeſſeth, that he promiſed his ayde in the ſame act.</p>
                     <p>Further he confeſſeth, that the time of the putting of the ſame in execution, was not yet determined,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5711:33"/>
but with opportunity, Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> would tell him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> in caſe that their intention had taken effect, they reſolved to kill all that ſhould make reſiſtance, and take the reſt Priſoners. And this was confirmed by <hi>Samuell Coulſons</hi> name.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Gabriell Towerſon,</hi> Agent for the Engliſh in Amboyna, of the age of 49. yeares, borne in London.</head>
                     <p>He confeſſeth, That he was in conference with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and with the others, hee tooke an oath vpon the Bible to be faithfull and ſecret.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he ſaith and confeſſeth, That he had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and divers times conſulted with his men for to make himſelfe Maſter of the Caſtle.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> hee confeſſeth, That all his men were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to it, and that he would haue put the ſame in execution the next time that the Governour <hi>Van Speult,</hi> had gone forth with his Curricuries.</p>
                     <p>Being asked what ſhould moue him therevnto, he anſwered, deſire of honor and profit.</p>
                     <p>Further being asked of whom hee looked to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that honor, and for whom he would haue kept the Caſtle, he anſwered, that if his intent had beene atchieved, he would haue informed thoſe of his Nation in <hi>Batavia,</hi> and require their aſſiſtance: the which being ſent him, he would haue kept the Caſtle for his Companie: but if they did not, hee would haue kept it for himſelfe, and ſeeke ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the <hi>Blacks,</hi> and ſo by ſome way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5711:34"/>
haue had his intent.</p>
                     <p>He confeſſeth moreover, That he gaue order to his men for to get him men and companions to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the ſame; as M. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> M. <hi>Iohnſon, Iohn Clarke</hi> and <hi>Abell Price,</hi> and they had already negotiated with the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers.</p>
                     <p>Hee ſaith, That the <hi>Iaponezes</hi> were twice in his houſe, but that he himſelf did not ſpeake with them but he cauſed them to be treated with by others.</p>
                     <p>He ſaith, That as yet he did not appoint the time becauſe it was too ſoone.</p>
                     <p>He ſaith, when time ſhould come convenient, he would to this intent haue ſent for all his men and ſlaves from the other Factories.</p>
                     <p>Further he ſaith, that no perſon whatſoever gaue him any order, inſtruction, or charge for the ſaid buſineſſe, but onely he was the firſt inventer and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this enterprize and plot, for the reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> he confeſſeth, That on New-yeares day laſt he conſulted with the Merchants, and thoſe of his Family concerning the taking of the Caſtle, and made them all ſweare vpon the Bible to be faithfull and ſecret.</p>
                     <p>Further he confeſſeth, that he hath not given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny order to any perſon whatſoever, to confer with thoſe of <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, Hitto,</hi> or <hi>Cambello,</hi> concerning this matter. So farre was he from promiſing them any powder, Ordnance, Bullets or Muskets, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ammunition of warre, at the arrivall of the Ships. Signed <hi>Gabriell Towerſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:5711:34"/>
                     <head>The Confeſson of <hi>Emanuel Tompſon</hi> Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> borne in <hi>Hamburrough,</hi> of the age of 50. yeares.</head>
                     <p>He confeſſeth, That on New-yeares day laſt paſt, a day after or before, hee, with other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants was ſent for to the chamber of <hi>Captaine To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werſon,</hi> and that the ſaid <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> then ſaid vnto them, that hee had a buſineſſe to impart vnto them, but firſt they muſt take their oathes vpon the Bible to be faithfull and ſecret to him; the which they all did.</p>
                     <p>Afterwards <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> told them in what manner the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were eſteemed in that Country, and that every where they muſt be the loweſt, and that they could not receiue juſtice in any kinde, and that he had found a way to be revenged thereof, and that he could be Maſter of the Caſtle if they would aſſiſt him. Vnto the which they all agreed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> the ſaid <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> ſaid, that thoſe of <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> would come with certaine <hi>Curicorrowes</hi> to aſſiſt him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item</hi> hee ſaith, that eight dayes after the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> told him, that hee had ſent M. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> and M. <hi>Price</hi> forth to treate, and get the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers to conſent to the ſame.</p>
                     <p>Further hee confeſſeth, that after the ſaid confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, he had ſundry times asked <hi>Captaine Towerſon</hi> how he proceeded in the buſineſſe, but he was ſtill anſwered, that he ſhould content himſelfe, and leaue the buſines to thoſe that were wiſer then himſelfe; and that he ſhould take heed, leaſt by his drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5711:35"/>
the buſineſſe ſhould be diſcovered. Signed <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuell Tompſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Iohn Wetherall</hi> Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, dwelling at <hi>Cambello,</hi> borne at <hi>Glaſton</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Rutland,</hi> aged 31. yeares.</head>
                     <p>Confeſſeth, That he was at the conference with others on New-yeares day, and tooke his oath as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did on the Bible, to be faithfull and ſecret.</p>
                     <p>That Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> after he had told them, how that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had indured a great deale of wrong by the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> and that he with the ayde of the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers and with the <hi>Blacks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> knew a way how to get the Caſtle, if they would all ayde him: they preſently promiſed to doe it.</p>
                     <p>This exploit ſhould haue beene put in execution when their ſhips ſhould haue arrived.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> He confeſſeth that the next day they were againe aſſembled, to animate and encourage one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in the advancement of their deſigne. Signed <hi>Iohn Wetherall.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Iohn Paul</hi> Aſsiſtant to the Engliſh at <hi>Cambello,</hi> borne in <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> aged 31. yeares.</head>
                     <p>Saith, that he hath not beene neere the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna</hi> this fiue moneths, &amp; that he knoweth not any thing therein.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Thomas Sharke,</hi> borne at <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> aged 36. yeares.</head>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:5711:35"/>Saith, That hee hath not beene in <hi>Amboyna</hi> this ſix moneths, and that he knoweth nothing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="confession">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Auguſtine Peres Marinho</hi> Captaine of the Slaves, aged 36. yeares, borne in <hi>Bengala.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Confeſſeth, That two moneths ſince, he was as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by a <hi>Iaponeze</hi> called <hi>Hytieſo</hi> in the name of <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Towerſon</hi> if hee would together with the <hi>Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezes</hi> aſſiſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the taking of the Caſtle the which he conſented to. Thus confeſſed in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> the 3. of <hi>March</hi> 1623.</p>
                     <p>The Worſhipfull <hi>Harman Van Speult</hi> Councellor in the <hi>Indies,</hi> Governour in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> &amp;c. having ſeene and vnderſtood the conformable confeſſions of divers perſons and Nations, being kept in divers places, and examined at divers times; doth not think any wayes neceſſarie by reaſon of the enormitie of the offence, that the cauſe could, nor ought not to ſuffer any reference: becauſe at the preſent they were charged with more then 40. Priſoners, and they did not know what enemies might be beſides, either within or without. Yet notwithſtanding, for the abundant ſatisfaction of the Honourable <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Companie</hi> and Nation, it was thought ſit to bee debated by Councell, whether the cauſe could ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any referring, or no.</p>
                     <p>Wherevpon by a generall voyce it was judged and reſolved, that the fact and crime ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the place where it was conceived and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5711:36"/>
for example to others: and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe at the preſent the <hi>Tarnatans</hi> and <hi>Mores</hi> herea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts contrary to their cuſtome, did a while ſince (in likelihood by the inſtigation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to rebell, and had ſlaine and killed certaine of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Nation, and ſervants of the Companie. Therefore his Worſhip cauſed the <hi>Fiſcall Brune</hi> for to forme ſuch demaund and concluſion againſt the ſaid Priſoners, as in reaſon he ſhould thinke fitting. Thus done, and reſolved the 8 of <hi>March</hi> 1623. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeumen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="proceedings">
                     <p>Whereas by the preceedent Acts and confeſſions it appeares ſufficiently, that <hi>Gabriell Towerſon</hi> Agent for the Honourable <hi>Engliſh Companie</hi> in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> with his creatures and Confederates aforeſaid, hath
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5711:36"/>
committed treaſon, and ſought the overthrow of the <hi>State,</hi> of the priviledged Company of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> in <hi>Amboyna;</hi> wherein depends the greateſt part of the proſperitie of the ſaid Company: and by a horrible murder and efuſion of bloud, wholy to ruinate the ſame; Therefore the Advocate <hi>Fiſcall Iſaack Brune, nomine officij,</hi> forming his Demaund, concludes, that the ſaid <hi>Gabriell Towerſon</hi> with all the other Delinquents, as well <hi>Engliſh</hi> as <hi>Iaponezes,</hi> aboue named (except <hi>Ephraim Iohn Paul</hi> Aſſiſtant to the <hi>Engliſh, Thomas Sharke,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Sadler</hi>) ſhould be carried to the place accuſtomed for exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Law and Iuſtice, and that they ſhould there be beheaded, and put to death with the confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of all their goods. And that the ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> after his death ſhould be cut in foure quarters, and his head ſhould bee ſet vp vpon the Gate vpon a pole, &amp; every-quarter ſhould be fixed vpon a Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet. Done in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna</hi> the 8. of <hi>March,</hi> 1623. And it was ſigned <hi>Iſaack de Brune</hi> Advocate <hi>Fiſcall.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Worſhipfull <hi>Harman Van Speult,</hi> Councellor of the <hi>Indies,</hi> Governour of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> &amp;c. with the ordinary Councell of his Worſhip, as alſo thoſe in the ſhips named the <hi>Rotterdam, Amsterdam,</hi> the <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne, Edam,</hi> and the <hi>Little-Hope,</hi> having heard the demaund and concluſion of the Advocate <hi>Fiſcall de Brune,</hi> made againſt the ſaid Delinquents, after they had called vpon the name of God, that hee would be pleaſed to aſſiſt them in their courſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this heavie aſſembly, and to inſpire into them nothing but equitie and juſtice, after mature conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5711:37"/>
in all that was neceſſary. To you the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents aſwell <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as <hi>Iaponezes;</hi> to wit, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Gabriell Towerſon, Samuell Coulſon, Emanuell Tompſon, Timothy Iohnſon, William Grigs, Iohn Clarke Abell Price, Robert Browne, Iohn Wetherall, Iohn Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, Augustine Peres Marinho.</hi> The Slaues, <hi>Hytie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, Sidney Migiell, Pedro Conge, Thome Corea, Tſioſa, Quiandao, Sinſa, Tſavienda,</hi> and <hi>Zancheo.</hi> Declare that you having committed treaſon, having concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and complotted together a horrible maſſacre &amp; treaſon, to bee Maſters of the Caſtle, and ſo haue compaſſed not onely to overthrow and ruinate the State of the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> in the vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> which the conſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this place much concerneth: but alſo to rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the Vnited <hi>Low-Countries</hi> themſelues, and their proſperities; partly conſiſting in Navigation and trafficke to the <hi>Indies,</hi> which by this meanes would haue beene vndermined and weakened. In purſuite whereof, and in the name, and in the qualitie of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the high and mighty Lords the <hi>States,</hi> Generall of the Vnited Provinces of the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> haue condemned the ſaid Delinquents, as by theſe preſents we condemne them, to be carried to the place where Law and Iuſtice is ordinarily exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and there to be puniſhed with the ſword in ſuch ſort as death may enſue: with the confiſcation according to the Law of their goods proper and in particular. And the heads of <hi>Gabriell Towerſon, Sid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Migiell, Hytieſo,</hi> and <hi>Pedro Conge,</hi> for example vnto others ſhall be ſet vpon poles.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Thus pronounced in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> 
                           <date>the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5711:37"/>
ninth day of <hi>March,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred twenty three.</date>
                        </dateline> 
                        <signed> And it was ſubſcribed
<list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                              </item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="proceedings">
                     <p>Whereas the ſaid Governour <hi>Van Speult</hi> for the ſervice of the honourable <hi>Engliſh</hi> Companie, hath thought good to ſpare two of the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants <hi>Pro tempore,</hi> for the grace and pardon of the Lord Governour Generall <hi>Peter de Carpentier,</hi> to the end that with other Deputies of his Worſhip they might looke to the goods of the ſaid honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Engliſh</hi> Companie. His Worſhip for certaine reaſons hath choſen for one of them <hi>Iohn Beomont, Engliſh</hi> Merchant in the Factorie of <hi>Lohoe.</hi> And or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth that M. <hi>Collins,</hi> M. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> and M. <hi>Coulſon</hi> ſhould draw lots betweene them three, which of them ſhould enjoy the like favour. Declaring not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5711:38"/>
that their proper goods ſhall bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly confiſcated according as the others. And his Worſhip pardoned <hi>Ephraim Iohn Paul, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Sharke,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Sadler,</hi> as having little and no knowledge of the ſaid plot. Done and reſolved the 8. of <hi>March</hi> 1623.</p>
                     <p>Maſter <hi>Coulſon, Thomſon,</hi> and <hi>Collins,</hi> being brought in a place together, and the Lots being preſented to them, after a ſhort prayer which every one made, they drew: firſt M. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> next M. <hi>Collins,</hi> and laſt M. <hi>Coulſon:</hi> the which being opened, it fell to M. <hi>Collins</hi> to be ſaved. Done in the Caſtle of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna</hi> the day aforeſaid. Subſcribed.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="proceedings">
                     <p>Whereas <hi>Augustine Peres Marinho</hi> of the Slaues, had knowledge of the treaſon and conſpiracy afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5711:38"/>
and being that he promiſed his ayde, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded of him, as is aforeſaid: and that the wife of <hi>Auguſtine Peres</hi> which hath beene a Slaue of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Dutch Eaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> India</hi> Company, who was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the ſaid <hi>Augustine</hi> in hope of his good car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, for the preſent, ſhee ſhall returne to her anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Maiſters of the ſaid Companie, vntill ſuch time that ſhee ſhall be otherwiſe diſpoſed of by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. Done in the Councell of <hi>Amboyna</hi> the 9. of <hi>March</hi> 1623. And was ſubſcribed.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iscobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell.</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſon Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="proceedings">
                     <p>We here vnder-named, doe declare for a truth in ſtead of an oath, that <hi>Gabriell Towerſon</hi> after he was examined concerning the ſaid plot, and the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>Van Speult</hi> condoling with him for that which is aforeſaid, asking him if that was the recompence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5711:39"/>
of his former friendſhip ſhewed to the ſaid <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi> The ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> with a deepe ſigh anſwered him and ſaid, alas! if it were to beginne againe, it ſhould never be done.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>Done the 9. of <hi>March,</hi>
                           </date> in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                        </dateline> 
                        <signed> Subſcribed.
<list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Peter Van Zanten,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="proceedings">
                     <p>The 9. of <hi>March</hi> 1623. in the Caſtle of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna</hi> it was reſolved; That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners that were for the preſent reſerved to the pardon of the Lord Generall <hi>de Carpentier,</hi> as M. <hi>Beomont,</hi> and M. <hi>Collins,</hi> as likewiſe thoſe that had none or little knowledge in the ſaid intended Treaſon, ſhould be againe remitted to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> lodgings, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers appointed by the Governour <hi>Van Speult,</hi> to keepe and looke to the goods of their Companie, vntill the arrivall of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Shippe, for to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thereof, as ſhould be found moſt neceſſary and profitable for the ſaid Companie.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Thus done in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna</hi> 
                           <date>the day aboue written.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.
<list>
                              <item>Harman Van Speult,</item>
                              <item>Laurence de Marſchalck,</item>
                              <item>Clement Kerſſeboom,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iohnſon Viſcher,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Leeuwen,</item>
                              <item>
                                 <pb n="37" facs="tcp:5711:39"/>Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop,</item>
                              <item>Leonard Clocq,</item>
                              <item>Martin Iohnſon Vogell;</item>
                              <item>Iohn Iooſten,</item>
                              <item>Iacob Cooper,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Peter Ianſen Van Zantem,</item>
                              <item>Harman Crayevanger,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Tailler,</item>
                              <item>Vincent Corthals <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>Vnder was written, collationed with the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and found to agree with the ſame in ſubſtance.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Done the 29. of <hi>March,</hi> 1623.</date> in the Caſtle of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna.</hi>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed> Subſcribed.
Fredericke Houtman, Martin Souck, Iohn Iacobſon Wincoop, Garrit Fredericke, Delbit Vesterman, Laurence de Marſchalck, Iohn Van Leeuwen, Leonard Clocq, Iſaack Migielſon Bogace, Peter Ianſen Van Zanten.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </postscript>
                  </div>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <p>Wee whoſe names are here vnder-written, being ſervants vnto the honourable <hi>Engliſh</hi> Companie in the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> having beene required by the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull <hi>Harman Van Speult</hi> Governour of <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> to examine the proceſſe of Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> and his Complices, being written in <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</hi> Wee haue heard and read the ſaid Proceſſe in two Languages, and according to our judgements, and as we can comprehend it, the ſubſtance of both the tranſlations agree in ſubſtance. </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Thus done in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5711:40"/>
the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna</hi>
                           <date> the 23. of <hi>May</hi> 1623. <hi>Stil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> Angliae.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline> And is ſubſcribed by thoſe whoſe names hereafter follow. To wit;
<signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Richard Welding.</item>
                              <item>Iohn Cartwright,</item>
                              <item>Henry Gill,</item>
                              <item>Iohn Van Nieupoort,</item>
                              <item>Rowland Hollers,</item>
                              <item>George Williams.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>Collation being made of this Tranſlation with the Authentick Copy ſent from the <hi>Indies,</hi> and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed as aforeſaid, is found to agree therewith. The 12. of <hi>August</hi> 1624.</p>
                        <p>By me the Secretarie of the <hi>States</hi> Generall, of the <hi>Vnited Provinces.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>I. Van Goch.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </postscript>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5711:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>A REPLY TO THE REMONSTRANCE of the Bewinthebbers or Directors of the Netherlands <hi>East-India</hi> Companie lately exhibited to the Lords States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, in iuſtification of the proceedings of their Officers at AMBOYNA, againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there.</head>
                  <p>THe Directors of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> 
                     <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, finding it needful to defend their Officers at <hi>Amboyna</hi> by this <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> referre themſelues in the firſt place vnto a former deduction which they had exhibited vnto the <hi>Lords States</hi> in <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt: Wherein they profeſſe ſtill to inſiſt. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering (ſay they) the infallible <hi>Indicia</hi> that prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the diſcouerie of this conſpiracy, and the iuſt and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5711:41"/>
Legall proceedings vſed againſt the Complices, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing by the iuditiall acts ſigned aſwell by the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties examined, as by the <hi>Gouernor and Councell</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> who are a <hi>Colledge</hi> or <hi>Court</hi> of Iudges admitted and ſworne; againſt which no proofe, much leſſe any vaine and friuolous ſuſpitions ought to be admitted, they therefore conceived (vntill they ſee the contrary) that the <hi>Conſperators</hi> (as they call them) were lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and rightly apprehended, the fact well prooued, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law and Cuſtome of the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> and conſequently that the puniſhment was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inflicted, with moderation of the rigour of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and with clemency.</p>
                  <p>This deduction of the moneth of <hi>Iuly</hi> heere men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, hath not beene yet imparted to the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt-India Companie.</hi> Otherwiſe they would haue exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the ſame, as they did the Relation printed in the Scheme of a letter Miſſive. Which yet they veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue to be the verie ſame in effect, and compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the ſame pen; for that it appeareth by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of the printed Pamphlet, with the Acts of this Proceſſe at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> here mentioned (copie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was communicated to the ſaid <hi>Engliſh Companie</hi>) that the body of the ſaid Pamphelet, (the preamble excepted) was wholie taken out of the ſame acts; onely with ſome ſophiſtication, of the act touching Maſter <hi>Towerſons</hi> pretended voluntarie confeſſion, noted in the <hi>Anſwere</hi> to the ſame Pamphlet. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although it may be ſuppoſed that this deduction here referred vnto, is already ſufficiently anſwered in the ſaid anſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation; yet becauſe in this very recitall of the <hi>Directors,</hi> there are certaine generall heads, either recapitulated out of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5711:41"/>
or laid for new grounds of the juſtification of the <hi>Dutch</hi> proceedings; it will not be amiſſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine them as they lie.</p>
                  <p>And firſt for the infallible <hi>Indicia</hi> pretended to haue preceaded the diſcouery; it is ſhewed in the anſwere to the Pamphlet, that the <hi>Indicia</hi> to torture the firſt <hi>Iapon</hi> (which was the beginning of the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe) were inſufficient in law: the behauiour that this <hi>Iapon</hi> vſed, and vpon which he was apprehended, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none other, then that which is and may be vſed by any Souldier in the place where he ſerueth, without blame or ſuſpicion. For other <hi>Indicia,</hi> there was not the leaſt; neither of prouiſions of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for ſuch an exployte, nor of Letters to or from any <hi>Complice,</hi> nor of ſuſpitious conferences, meſſages, or intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, nor of flight or cloſe keeping of the parties; nor any other agreeing with the rules or examples giuen by the Law, or the Authors commenting thereupon. But being deſtitute of theſe and the like lawfull <hi>Indicia,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Officers were faine to fetch their <hi>Indicia</hi> out of the <hi>Racke,</hi> and to make the confeſſion of one tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red perſon <hi>Indicium</hi> to torture another, contrary to the very expreſſe direction of the Law. Some confeſſions indeed, were without actuall torture of the perſons themſelues: but euen ſuch had heard the cryes and ſeene the bodies of others tortured and martyred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; which feare of the <hi>Torture</hi> is by the Law e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled to the torture it ſelfe, as hath beene ſhewed in the ſaid anſwere.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond generall ground here layd, is the juditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all acts of the Colledge of Iudges at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> ſhewing their juſt and legall proceedings. The Acts indeed of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5711:42"/>
any Court of Iuſtice being orderly kept, yeeld a very ſufficient proofe in the point of fact in Court: that is, they prooue that ſuch and ſuch examinations, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, proofes, and euidences were taken and made; and ſuch iudgement thereupon giuen as is therein en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. But for the point of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that muſt be judged by the comparing of the proofes with the ſentence grounded vpon them. Now as touching the orderly keeping of theſe <hi>Acts</hi> imparted to the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt India</hi> Company as aforeſaid: the ſame are neither agreeable to the formes of other Courts, nor vniforme in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For the point of conformitie to other Courts, it is not here meant to require, that the Acts of the Councell of <hi>Amboyna</hi> ſhould in euery point agree with the formes of euery Court in the <hi>Low Countryes;</hi> the ſeuerall Courts whereof haue their ſeuerall formes and ſtile, and ſome differences in points not ſubſtantiall. But ſome generall Requiſites of forme there be, which are obſerued in all Courts; yet omitted in theſe <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> As firſt the date of euery dayes paſſages ought to be prefixed or annexed vnto them; which is not obſerued in theſe ſaid Acts. But in theſe Acts the examination of all the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> being 18 ſeuerall priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, goeth vnder the date of the 25. of <hi>Februarie:</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the confeſſions are ſo many and ſo large, as could not poſſibly be taken in one day: yea three of the ſame priſoners, to wit, <hi>Powle, Wether all,</hi> and <hi>Ladbrooke</hi> were but apprehended firſt vpon the 26. of <hi>February,</hi> and that at <hi>Cambello</hi> the outmoſt factory in <hi>Seran,</hi> and arriued not at <hi>Amboyna</hi> (where theſe examinations were taken) vntill the ſecond of <hi>March ſtilo nouo.</hi> So that they could not be examined at <hi>Amboyna</hi> the 25. of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5711:42"/>
                     <hi>February</hi> as the Acts import. Next, it is a ſolennitie in all Courts, to note in the Acts, the day of the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the <hi>Priſoner</hi> vpon the <hi>Torture,</hi> or in the place of the <hi>Torture;</hi> and then the act of his ſubſcription to his confeſſion vpon another day. For theſe two may not be done vpon the ſame day by the Law: but the confeſſion muſt be iterated and confirmed by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner being free of bonds and irons, at leaſt a day after the ſence or ſight of the torture: els it is not held for good, and concluding againſt the partie that confeſſed it. But in all theſe Acts of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> there is but one date and one Act for both theſe: contrary to the Law it ſelfe, and the Cuſtome and forme of all Courts. Thirdly, the Acts ought to ſpecifie whether the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner confeſſeth vpon <hi>Torture</hi> or without. But theſe Acts doe not ſo: but onely in the generall; in the beginning of the Acts of the 26. of <hi>February,</hi> it is entred, that ſome confeſſed before <hi>Torture,</hi> others with little <hi>Torture</hi> as followeth, &amp;c. Whereby it appeareth not, who was tortured and who not; nor what was confeſſed with, and what without torture. Fourthly, the Acts ought to ſpecifie what finally becometh of euery priſoner; but in theſe Acts there is no entry made what became of <hi>Sherrocke, Webber,</hi> and two of the <hi>Iapons,</hi> to wit, <hi>Soyſimo</hi> and <hi>Sacoube;</hi> theſe being by the Acts neither condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor abſolued, nor repriued; and yet all foure are <hi>de facto</hi> diſmiſſed and ſet at libertie.</p>
                  <p>As for the point of Vniformitie in the Acts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <hi>Collins</hi> and <hi>Beamount</hi> are diſpoſed of by ſpeciall Act; yet <hi>Sherrock, Webber,</hi> and the two <hi>Iapons</hi> (all in the ſame caſe) are diſcharged, as before, without any Act for it. Yea there is an Act entred for diſpoſing of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5711:43"/>
                     <hi>Portugalls</hi> wife, though ſhee were neither accuſed nor examined: as if ſhee had beene a partie to the Proceſſe, rather then <hi>Sherrock, Webber,</hi> and theſe two <hi>Iapons,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all whom the <hi>Fiſcall</hi> craued judgment. Further, ſome of the Examinations haue the Gouernour and his Councels names ſubſcribed to them, and ſome not: ſome of the confeſſions haue the priſoners names ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and ſome not; with diuers other defects and diſconformities, which eaſily and plainely diſcouer that they are not allowable for orderly and authenticall <hi>Acts</hi> of a <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus hath beene ſhewed what credit may be giuen to theſe Acts in the point of fact therein recorded. Now for the point of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> appearing by comparing the proofes againſt the priſoners with the ſentence, it is in the firſt place to be noted, that there is no proofe nor euidence of any thing entred in all the ſaid Acts, no not ſo much as a witneſſe named, much leſſe depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, of the leaſt <hi>Indicium</hi> againſt the priſoners, or any of them; but onely the meere confeſſions of the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners themſelues, drawne from them by the paine or juſt feare of torture. Which meere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of the parties, without other <hi>Indiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> or proof, is no ſufficient ground to condemne any by the Law of the <hi>Low Countryes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is a <hi>Requiſite</hi> of their Law, that the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners ſubſcribe their confeſſions being free of bonds and irons. Now neither is there any mention in all the Acts of any ſuch free confeſſion, and all our people that eſcaped are ready to confirme vpon their oathes, that from the firſt apprehenſion vntill the houre of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the execution, there was no intermiſſion of the fetters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5711:43"/>Thirdly, the ſame confeſſions are full of contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: as one while that the plott ſhould be executed when ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhip or ſhippes ſhould be there ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued, the people whereof ſhould aſſiſt in the exployt: another while, that when the Caſtle was taken, then Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> would firſt ſend to <hi>Iaccatra</hi> for aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Likewiſe, one while that it ſhould be attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted when the <hi>Dutch</hi> Gouernor was abroad vpon ſome enterprize: another while that the Gouernor himſelfe ſhould be killed in the Caſtle. Further, one while that all the <hi>Iapons</hi> were wonne to the plotte before Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> opened it to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and conſulted with them; another while, that he ſent out ſome of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> eight dayes after that conſultation, then to winne the <hi>Iapons.</hi> Alſo one while that the <hi>Iapons</hi> had conſulted diuers times with Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> himſelfe in the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> houſe; another while that they neuer treated with Maſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> himſelfe, but with others in his name; with other like contradictions, differences, and incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties. Further, the place, perſons and time were ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to <hi>Abel Price</hi> in his examination, contrary to the Law. In the laſt place the thing confeſſed to be plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, was not onely impoſſible to be atchieued by ſuch meanes and manner of execution as was confeſſed: but as impoſſible alſo to come into the imagination of any man in his witts: as is already ſufficiently ſhewed in the anſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation. By which premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes appeareth, that as well through defect of other proofe, beſides the meere confeſſions of the priſoners, and that in Irons; as in reſpect of the incertaintie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, and contrarietie of the ſame confeſſions, the ſpecification and leading examinations, together
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5711:44"/>
with the impoſſibilitie of the truth of the thing confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, there is in theſe Acts no lawful ground for the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemnation.</p>
                  <p>The third generall ground that is laid in this Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance is, that the Acts were ſigned by the priſoners themſelues, and by the Councell of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> which is a Court or Colledge of Iudges admitted and ſworne: and therefore no proofes, much leſſe any vaine and friuolous ſuſpitions may be admitted to the contrary.</p>
                  <p>As for the ſubſcription of the Priſoners to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions; of what value that is without other <hi>Indicia</hi> and proofes hath beene already declared. Now that no proofes may be admitted againſt ſworne Iudges, is a ſtrange <hi>Maxime:</hi> which being granted muſt needs inferre either that ſuch Iudges cannot erre and judge vniuſtly; or elſe that how euer they carry themſelues, their doings muſt not be examined, much leſſe puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. So that then the Law hath in vaine prouided puniſhment for a Iudge in caſe of wrong impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, cauſleſſe vnorderly torture, and of vniuſt abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or condemning, and the like; for which there are ſo many and ſo diligent prouiſions. It may be thought indeed, that vnder this confidence this whole Proceſſe was begun and followed; as the ſafeſt and faireſt way to be ridd of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> without ſuch reckoning as was formerly made for the courſes of open hoſtilitie. But if this way goe for currant, though towards a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Nation: how comes it that by the Law and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of Nations, ſo many Reprizalles and warres haue been made for iniuſtice done by the Iudges of one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the people of another, when none other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe could be obtained, yea and many times in ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5711:44"/>
foule cauſes as this, without any demand of redreſſe?</p>
                  <p>Theſe grounds aforeſaid, being thus laid, this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> proceedeth to take notice of two ſeuerall Diſcourſes ſpread as well in <hi>England</hi> as in the <hi>Lowe Countryes</hi> againſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> cauſe of <hi>Amboyna:</hi> the firſt, a briefe Collection of the effect of certaine Letters written by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factors at <hi>Iaccatra,</hi> dated the 19. of <hi>Iune</hi> 1623. The ſecond, a more ample Writing, entituled, <hi>A true Relation of the cruell and barbarous Tortures and Execution of the Engliſh at Amboyna by the Dutch there.</hi> The former of theſe this <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> chargeth with paſſion and great vehemency; becauſe it doth by way of preiudice, enſtile the Proceſſe of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> an vniuſt and barbarous murder: and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauateth the faſhion and manner of the Tortures. So it vouchſafeth this none other anſwere; but this note of paſſion; and that it falſely nameth the <hi>Iapons</hi> executed to be the ſeruants of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> Whereas in truth they were the ſeruants of the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Amboyna.</hi> What or whoſe this Diſcourſe thus excepted againſt and thus anſwered is; the <hi>Engliſh Company</hi> knowes not. Yet they beleeue not that any of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> partie, would (except it were by a ſlip of the penne) call theſe <hi>Iapons,</hi> ſeruants of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> the ſame being contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all the reports and aduertiſements that came from <hi>Amboyna</hi> and <hi>Iaccatra;</hi> it is likewiſe to be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that if in that Writing there had beene any thing els, which they could haue anſwered, they would not haue diſmiſſed it as they doe. For, as for the terming the execution, <hi>An vniuſt and barbarous murder;</hi> that were no more cauſe to reiect the Diſcourſe without further anſwere; then the like ſtile giuen it in the very
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5711:45"/>
title of the ſecond and larger Writing, which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe hath obtained a more particular anſwere.</p>
                  <p>Hauing giuen the firſt Writing this quicke diſpatch,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> proceedeth to the anſwere of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſet out by the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt India Company;</hi> and in the firſt place chargeth it with an impertinent deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (in the very introduction) of the Caſtle of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Garriſons and Forces there; to the end (ſaith this <hi>Remonſtrance</hi>) to ſhew that there was no likelihood nor probability that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there would vndertake the ſurprize of the Caſtle; being a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be done: as if (ſaith the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi>) the want of vnderſtanding in the Conſpirators, and the fooliſh ground of their proiect (all other accuſations ceaſing) ſhould haue excuſed them from puniſhment: the contrary whereof is euery where obſerued.</p>
                  <p>Here in the very firſt ſteppe of the Anſwere, the end of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company in ſetting out the impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the fact, is either miſtaken or traduced. For if the conſpiracy had beene ſufficiently prooued according to the direction euen of the Lawes by which the <hi>Dutch</hi> are gouerned; then the probabilitie or poſſibilitie of the fact had neuer beene alledged. For in ſuch caſe it is true, that the fooliſhneſſe of the plott excuſeth no man. But when there is no other proofe or euidence, but the meere confeſſion of the priſoner, (which is the preſent caſe) then the very text of the Law of treaſon, enioyneth the Iudge to conſider the perſon of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner (<hi>which is the preſent caſe) then the very text of the Law of Treaſon, enioyneth the Iudge to conſider the perſon of the priſoner;</hi> whether he be able to execute ſuch a thing as he is accuſed of, whether he euer practiſed the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5711:45"/>
like before; what he meant; and whether he were in his wits of no; and ſuch like; For without theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations the ſlippery confeſſion of the tongue ought not to be the ground of the puniſhment. This is their Law, according to which if they had proceeded, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had neuer needed to alledge theſe impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; which the Iudges themſelues ought to haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. But not hauing done it, they haue made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues guiltie of vniuſt Iudgement; which to prooue, the impoſſibilitie of the fact is both pertinent and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
                  <p>But the better to inforce the former anſwere, the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> ſaith, that this preſumption of the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of the fact ought not to be conſidered, againſt a veritie altogether notorious and prooued, againſt the confeſſions of the priſoners themſelues, and againſt the conſcience &amp; teſtimony of ſo many men of worth and credit, that managed this affayre, and againſt a Court or Colledge of Iudges, &amp;c. in publique Office and ſworne.</p>
                  <p>All this is but a Rhetoricall flouriſh, and being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, will vaniſh into the ayre as a meere ſound. For firſt for the notoriouſneſſe of the pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie; although now <hi>ex poſt facto,</hi> they cry it out for notorious; yet at the time when the notorietie ſhould haue beene conſidered, which was before the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, torturing, and execution of our people; there was not the leaſt breath of ſuch a fame. It is now too late to alledge a notorietie, that themſelues haue made who alledge it. As for the proofes here mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; Why haue they not at any time ſpecified them? If there be none other proofes beſides the meere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5711:46"/>
(as other the Acts doe not ſo much as menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) why then are proofes and confeſſions here diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acumulated; as if there were any other proofes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſaid confeſſions? As for the conſcience and teſtimony of thoſe that managed the Proceſſe, being a publique and ſworne Colledge of Iudges; it is not at all to be reckoned of; when it appeareth that they haue not proceeded according to the Law. And if this plea might be admitted, no Iudge ſhould euer be found guiltie of Iniuſtice. Further, if the very qualitie of the Iudges be conſidered, it will rather hurt then helpe them: there were none amongſt them that had any ordinary knowledge in the Law, whereby they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to judge cauſes: beſides their young yeares and wicked liues: which if it were pertinent to the cauſe in queſtion, might be ſet forth by many ſpeciall inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But if they were neuer ſo learned, experienced, or well famed; yet that would not auayle when they haue proceeded againſt the preſcript of their owne Law (to ſay nothing here of the treatie) as they are ſufficiently prooued to haue done.</p>
                  <p>But this <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> not truſting to this Anſwere, in ſlighting the improbability and impoſſibility of the fact, as not worth the conſidering; yet for all that, in the next place laboureth and ſweateth to make the fact ſeeme probable and poſſible, the contrary whereof in vs that hold the contrary part, it reiecteth as imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; Is it impertinent for vs to ſhew the improbabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and impoſſibilitie of the fact; and yet pertinent for them to ſhew the contrary probabilitie and poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? But let vs ſee and conſider their preſumptions. Firſt (they ſay) they haue already proued, that the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5711:46"/>
for a diuerſion of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Forces in the Caſtle, had inuited and induced all the <hi>Ternatans, Seranians,</hi> and neighbouring <hi>Indians</hi> to rebell, and doe violence to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> that when the <hi>Dutch</hi> Gouernour ſhould haue drawne the maine of his Forces of men and ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that way, then the <hi>Engliſh</hi> might with eaſe take the Caſtle ſo emptied and denuded of her Forces.</p>
                  <p>How vaine this point is, is already manifeſted in the Anſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation. And as for the proofes here mentioned; there is in all the Acts not ſo much as any offer made of any proofe of this point.</p>
                  <p>But it is worthy againe to be noted, that here the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and <hi>Scene</hi> is changed. For where in the <hi>Dutch</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation it is ſaid, (though no where prooued) that the <hi>Ternatans</hi> of <hi>Loho</hi> ſhould haue come with their <hi>Curri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curryes</hi> to aſſiſt Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Gouernour muſt haue beene killed there in the Caſtle by the <hi>Iapons;</hi> now he muſt be gone with all his Forces out of the Iſland to tame thoſe <hi>Ternatans</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Seranians</hi> &amp; neighbouring <hi>Indians:</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> might ſurprize the Caſtle in their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. As for the ſhippes of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> which now alſo muſt haue beene abſent: it is well knowne, that the ſeruice here pretended would neither need, nor could haue vſe of their great ſhippes, but onely of Curry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curries and ſmall Veſſels, which alſo the <hi>Dutch</hi> after v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, leauing their great ſhipping in the roade by the Caſtle.</p>
                  <p>The ſtrength of the <hi>Dutch</hi> thus extenuated, in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> next place the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> purſuing the argument of poſſibilitie, amplifieth the Forces of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> And firſt it deliuereth, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had a great number
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5711:47"/>
of ſlaues in their Factories, which great number is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready truely confeſſed in the anſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to be iuſt ſixe and all boyes. Next it is added, that they would alſo haue ſtayed their actuall attempt of the Caſtle, vntill ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhippes were arriued there; which point is alſo at large refuted in the ſaid Anſwere. Thirdly, here is alledged, that Maiſter <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> had giuen charge vnto his other <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to haue daily laboured and wonne by vnder-hand practize, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubiects of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> thereby to augment their owne partie, and to weaken the ſtrength of the <hi>Dutch.</hi> Of which point, as there was no probabilitie; ſo in all the Acts, there is no ſhadow of proofe thereof made, or ſo much as endeuoured: how euer now the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate cauſe requireth the helpe of ſo groſſe a fiction. Fourthly (which is vaunted for the principall argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) it is here ſeriouſly obſerued; that the Caſtle ſhould haue beene ſurprized by treaſon and not by ſiege; and ſo like enough the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (though but few) might by this meanes doe wonders. A very poore note; as if the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Relation had cited impoſſibilities by way of ſiege, and not as well by way of trechery. But beſides that, this argument beggeth the maine queſtion; to wit, that there was indeed ſuch a treaſon: was there euer any ſuch treaſon or ſtratagem practized in any Countrey, to ſurprize a Caſtle by a ſmall force; without a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency of ſeconds to make good and hold that which was ſo entred and poſſeſſed? Yet this argument is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> enforced, not onely by the opportunitie that the <hi>Iapons</hi> had to betray the Caſtle; themſelues ſeruing as Souldiers therein; but alſo by the extraordinary valour ane hardineſſe of that Nation, ſet forth by two ſeuerall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5711:47"/>
Apochriphal Legends of ſtrange feats of other <hi>Iapons;</hi> without ſpecifying of the number of them that perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med theſe wonders, but leauing a blanke to helpe the tale at their pleaſure. But let it be granted that the <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons</hi> are all Gyants, and had opportunity being truſted: yet is it likely, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Gouernour in his expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here ſuppoſed againſt the Rebells of <hi>Seran</hi> and the other <hi>Indians,</hi> would haue left ſuch Worthies idle in their Caſtle at home, and not haue taken them with them, according to their Cuſtome? Would they haue withdrawne their <hi>Dutch,</hi> and truſted ſuch ſtrangers with their Caſtle, being yet ſo ſuſpitious of them, that they would torture them for asking an ordinary harmeleſſe queſtion? O miſerable preſumptions! And yet here we haue all the particulars that are alledged, or could be inuented.</p>
                  <p>In the next place, the Remonſtrants returne to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> anſwere of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation: finding themſelues grieued, that their Councell of <hi>Amboyna</hi> is charged to haue forged this crime againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> thereby to be ridd of their company, and ſo to enioy the trade there alone. For their purgation wherein, here are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers arguments alledged. As firſt, that if they had not liked their company there, it had beene eaſier and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to haue kept them out, when they were out, then to haue ſo caſt them out after their admiſſion of them by the Treatie, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1619. And God forbid (ſaith the <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi>) that any ſhould vſe ſuch wicked and bloudy meanes for ſo poore an end, as onely to driue the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is true ordinarily; <hi>Turpius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ijcitur &amp;c.</hi> It is more diſcurteſie to turne out a gueſt, then at firſt to deny
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5711:48"/>
him entertainment. But ſometimes there may be ſuch a neceſſitie, as that a man muſt needs, for avoyding of a greater inconuenience, entertaine the gueſt, whom he is as glad to be ridd of, as he was vnwilling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him. And ſometimes a man entertaineth a gueſt in hope of ſome benefit to be made by him; whereof afterwards being fruſtrate, he will gladly be quit of his gueſt as ſoone as he findeth himſelfe defeated of his hoped ends. Both theſe conſiderations haue had their place in this entertaining of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Amboyna</hi> and other places. For the former, all that are acquainted with the occaſion, and the paſſages of the Treatie of the yeare 1619. know very well, that there was then none other or better way or meane for the <hi>Hollanders Eaſt India Company</hi> to giue ſatisfaction to the <hi>Kings Maieſty</hi> for the bloud of many of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the inualuable damage done vnto the <hi>Engliſh Company</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Hollanders</hi> vniuſt taking of their ſhippes and goods onely in reſpect of their lawfull trade into the Iſlands of the <hi>Moluccoes</hi> and <hi>Banda;</hi> but the accommodation of the whole matter, by admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt India Company</hi> into the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the trade in thoſe Iſlands, and this of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna.</hi> Which being yeelded vnto with great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; yet the ſaid <hi>Dutch</hi> with might and maine reſerued the Forts which they were then poſſeſſed of, in their owne hands: thereby ſtill retaining the power and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to maſter the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and weary them of their lodging at their pleaſure. In the next place, it ſeemeth by their after-courſe that hauing ſo aſſured themſelues of the Forts and Maſtring power, they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to make benefit by this partnerſhip; by the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5711:48"/>
of their Accompts in ſuch manner, as that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould pay their part of the charge as well of the Garriſons as of their new buildings, and of the warres which they vndertooke for enlarging the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> Dominion, and all this in ready money, whileſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> furniſhed their owne ſhare in commodities, and at what prizes they liſt. Now when the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>Indies</hi> ſaw, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there would not ſuffer themſelues to be thus bridled and ſadled; but made their proteſts and complaints againſt this dealing: they ſought meanes to be quit of them. And finding that the blunt way of fact would not be well taken, but giue a new offence to the King, (eſpecially after the Treaty to the contrary) they deuiſe this new meane to thruſt out their vnwelcome gueſts, with leſſe bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed then they before had kept them out with, and with leſſe feare of accompting for the ſame, being done vnder the faire colour of Iuſtice; which point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clearely enough touched in the very Introduction of the <hi>Engliſh Relation,</hi> this <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> profeſſing an anſwere to the whole, yet paſſeth ouer this with a dry foote, and deepe ſilence: yea, it minceth the very matter whereof it ſeemes to take notice, making the charge againſt them to be onely the driuing of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> out of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh Relation</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them to haue contriued and executed this bloudy buſineſſe, with intention to driue them (the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) out of the <hi>Moluccoes</hi> and <hi>Banda</hi> alſo, as well as out of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> Which end and drift of the worke how euer it is ſlighted hereby the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> yet it appeareth of what value it is in their ſecret eſtimation, by that which they haue formerly done to keepe the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:5711:49"/>
from the trade of thoſe Iſlands.</p>
                  <p>Yet further to cleare themſelues of this end and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> they alledge that the <hi>Netherlands Eaſt India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> here in <hi>Europe</hi> neuer gaue any Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to their Officers at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> to put ſuch a thing as this in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, nor could haue any benefit thereby, but rather loſſe: and the Officers themſelues were too honeſt and wiſe to haue executed ſuch a Commiſſion: eſpecially ſince themſelues ſhould haue no profit by it, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre great danger of giuing accompt for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>For the point of Commiſſion, the <hi>Engliſh Companie</hi> doth not charge the <hi>Dutch Company,</hi> nor the whole Colledge of <hi>Directors,</hi> with any ſuch proiect or directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Neither doe they thinke that any one amongſt them would by his priuate aduice incite the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Amboyna</hi> to this or the like fact in particular. But they cannot tell whether ſome one or few amongſt them of ſpeciall place and authoritie; and of like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect with their Officers in the <hi>Indies,</hi> may not vpon ſome diſcontent or diſlike of the Treatie &amp; the effects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thereof, haue giuen aduice to the principall Officers of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>Indies,</hi> to lay hands and make vſe of any colourable occaſion, to weary the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of the trade eſtabliſhed by the Treatie; and ſo the Gouernor of <hi>Amboyna</hi> may haue fallen vpon this particular out of ſuch generall grounds of aduice. Which ſuſpition of the <hi>Engliſh Company,</hi> ariſeth not onely from the earneſt and ſtrayned defence and iuſtification which they now obſerue to be made of this execrable fact; but alſo from a paſſage that fell out here in <hi>London</hi> immediately after the Treatie <hi>An.</hi> 1619. which now this diſpute calleth to their remembrance. And here in they report them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5711:49"/>
to the memorie and conſcience of thoſe of the <hi>Dutch</hi> directors, that were then employed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of an explanation of the Articles of the Treatie, intituled; <hi>The Order of Execution, &amp;c.</hi> whether one of them appearing highly diſcontented, for that the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> would not condeſcend to a propoſition of theirs, about the order of ſelling out the Spices here in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> did not then in a vehement manner threaten the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (that dealt with them about that point) that they ſhould repent them of their diſſent herein: which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> not vnderſtanding by all the diſputes, how it could come to paſſe in the courſe of trade, if the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie were obſerued, ſtill perſiſted in their former reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whereupon the ſaid partie with the reſt of the <hi>Dutch</hi> deſired that it might be noted in the Iournall of the Conference; that they had forewarned them, that there would a great inconuenience follow by reaſon of this diſſent of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which was noted in the ſame Iournall accordingly. What this carriage might por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, or what directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s might be giuen in conſequence of this diſcontent, the <hi>Engliſh Company</hi> leaue to be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by others: hauing themſelues neuer ſince in the courſe of their ſale of the Spices, without obſeruation of the order (then deſired by the <hi>Dutch</hi>) found any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience but rather aduantage; As for the benefit of the <hi>Dutch</hi> by driuing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the trade of the <hi>Moluccoes, Banda,</hi> and <hi>Amboyna,</hi> it may be eſteemed (as is before noted) by the courſes that the <hi>Dutch</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly tooke to keepe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of that trade. And for their contrary benefit here alſo pretended by holding the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the communion of that trade: It is true, that as long as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would pay readie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5711:50"/>
money, the <hi>Dutch</hi> paying in wares, would beare their ſhare of the charge of Fortifications and Conqueſts, whereof the benefit accrued wholly to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as long as they would ioyne with the <hi>Dutch</hi> to finde the Enemy worke in one place, while the <hi>Dutch</hi> might thereby the eaſier winne for themſelues onely in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place: ſo long the <hi>Dutch</hi> might eaſily make bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their partnerſhip, and abide their ſharing with them for one third part of that trade. But when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhewed themſelues ſenſible of this <hi>Leonine</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, and proteſted againſt it, and refuſed to purſue the Action of defence in ſuch a courſe: Then it was time to ſeeke out an occaſion to be vtterly freed from their partnerſhip, now proouing otherwiſe then was before hoped. As touching the honeſtie of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers at <hi>Amboyna</hi> here alledged, there hath been enough ſaid alreadie. And for their benefit alſo by thus ridding themſelues of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who knoweth not what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit may be expected by being an Inſtrument of ſo great profit, atchieuing it by ſuch a conueyance, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in who euer giueth Commiſſion, is by ioynt guilt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to gratifie and promote his inſtrument euen for his owne ſafetie? Beſides, their Officers had their owne priuate quarrells againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for their daily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt their riotous liuing, and the great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence thereof, deriued in the greateſt part vpon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by the arts aboue-mentioned. Eſpecially the Gouernour himſelfe had a maine griefe, that the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> had often complained to the <hi>Councell</hi> of Defence at <hi>Iaccatra,</hi> of the extraordinary &amp; exceſſiue charge of his Table and other expences: which by the Iournal of the conſultations of the ſaid <hi>Councell</hi> appeareth to haue bin
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5711:50"/>
a matter of much diſpute there, and was at laſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the <hi>Dutch</hi> partie to be reformed. Another quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell alſo the ſame Gouernour had againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> about a <hi>Dutch-man</hi> that was executed for killing of an <hi>Engliſhman;</hi> Which <hi>Dutch-man</hi> when the Gouernour could not fairely ſaue (the fact being too foule and manifeſt to beare it) he was ſo offended with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> proſecution of the matter, that he ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vowed, if euer any of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> came within his compaſſe, ſuch ſhould repent that none of them had interceded for the life of the ſaid <hi>Dutch-man.</hi> Laſtly, it muſt be remembred, that at the time of this forged crime, the newes of the Match with <hi>Spaine</hi> was very rife and hott at <hi>Amboyna;</hi> where with how all the <hi>Dutch</hi> there were enraged, and what inſolent ſpeeches they vſed of the Kings Maieſtie, is well enough knowne; though thought vnmeete to be here recited.</p>
                  <p>Hauing thus laboured to cleare the finall cauſe of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="K"/> this Proceſſe, the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> returne to charge the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (that are executed) with other arguments of their pretended treaſon. As (ſay they) if it were not a true treaſon, why came the <hi>Iapon</hi> (that was firſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended vpon the walles) and made ſuch curious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition about the ſetting of the Watch, and of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Forces in the Caſtle? How came it that being examined, he forthwith ſpake ſo pertinently of this treaſon? If he were ſuborned by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> why then did they execute him? Why did he accuſe his owne Countrymen as well as the <hi>Engliſh?</hi> Why ſhould the <hi>Dutch</hi> thus vſe the <hi>Iapons,</hi> whom they had no cauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to hate?</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:5711:51"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5711:51"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5711:52"/>The firſt of theſe queſtions is already anſwered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to wit, that the <hi>Iapon</hi> did nothing herein, but what any Souldier may lawfully, and is wont to doe, without blame or iuſt ſuſpition. It importeth euery Souldier to know the ſtrength of the place where he ſerueth, and the order and courſe of the ſeruice, as is ſaid in the anſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation. The ſecond queſtion would be as eaſily anſwered, if it had ſeemed good to thoſe that kept the Acts, to haue kept faithfull Record in them of the Interrogatories miniſtred to this <hi>Iapon</hi> in his tortures. But the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation in the Examinations of <hi>Collins, Sherrock,</hi> and <hi>Beamont,</hi> hath diſcouered the Art vſed in all the reſt; to wit, the leading Interrogatories, or rather Directories, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to the priſoner what he might ſay to come quitt of the torture: As for the ſuborning of this <hi>Iapon</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> here mentioned in the third queſtion; The <hi>Engliſh</hi> eaſily grant that hee was not ſuborned, but (which is worſe) he was tortured to make him accuſe both the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and his owne Countrymen) the <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons;</hi> which alſo anſwereth the fourth queſtion of this Rhetoricall Dialogiſme. And for the fift and laſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, why the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhould alſo practiſe the <hi>Iapons</hi> deſtruction: it is eaſily conceiued, that els the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould haue ſeemed to haue had no Complices, nor hope of aſſiſtance of other Nations, which would haue made their crime appeare more impoſſible to be a true charge then now it doth; although (as now it is) it is vtterly voyde of all probabilitie and poſſibilitie. And is it any wonder they would ſacrifice the bloud of tenne Infidells for that end, for which they ſpared not tenne Chriſtians, and thoſe of that Nation which moſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5711:52"/>
with themſelues in Religion, and to whom they are of all other Nations moſt beholden?</p>
                  <p>In the next place, the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> proceedeth to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> anſwere a circumſtance related by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that the <hi>Iapons</hi> being examined three or foure dayes before them, they yet fled not: whereby they ſhewed their innocency. To the conſequence of which argument the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> firſt anſwereth, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did this to auoyde great ſuſpition, being ſure enough they could not fly: the Gouernour had (euen to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) taken ſuch order to ſtop all paſſages, as well of all other Merchants that then frequented <hi>Amboyna</hi> as of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is a meere fiction: for the Curricurries and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Veſſells departed as freely from <hi>Amboyna</hi> while the <hi>Iapons</hi> were in examination, as at any time before. And if the Gouernor had vſed neuer ſo much circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection herein, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had knowne of it, yet how could ſo many guiltie conſciences haue contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues, and not one of them all haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to flie or hide or diſguiſe himſelfe in all this time? All men know that a guiltie conſcience prouoketh men to attempteſcapes aboue and againſt all reaſon. And therefore the Law euer enquireth of the flight or ſhrinking of the accuſed as a ſpeciall <hi>indicium</hi> of their guilt. Why did not the <hi>Dutch</hi> then in their examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons queſtion and ſift out by what conſultation and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> came to be of one minde, to ſhew ſuch confidence in this caſe?</p>
                  <p>But to make a further and better anſwere to this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> chargeth the matter of it with vntruth: Saying that the examination of the <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:5711:53"/>
began the 24. of <hi>Februarie,</hi> and that the next day after, to wit, the 25. the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were ſeized; So that here was but one dayes reſpite for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to ſhift for themſelues.</p>
                  <p>This impudence is very ſtrange; for, the Acts of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> the Proceſſe record, the beginning of the examination of the <hi>Iapons</hi> to be the 23. of <hi>Februarie,</hi> and the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſeize the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to be the 26. which is the third day after <hi>incluſiuè.</hi> It is well wee haue a copie of their Acts, (ſuch as they are) els we ſee into how many formes this <hi>Proteus</hi> would turne, to auoyde the true diſcouery.</p>
                  <p>After this the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> with the like modeſtie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> note another vntruth in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation, where it affirmeth that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had not any conuerſation with the <hi>Iapons;</hi> the contrary whereof (ſay the <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants</hi>) appeareth as well by the confeſſions of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> as the <hi>Iapons,</hi> and particularly by Maiſter <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> voluntary confeſſion, made long time after his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.</p>
                  <p>What credit the Acts and confeſſions may deſerue, is alreadie ſhewed: and the very perſons themſelues therein aſſigned to this conuerſation with the <hi>Iapons,</hi> had no language to ſerue them therein. And for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Towerſons</hi> voluntary confeſſion pretended to be made ſo many dayes after his examination; beſides the foule play of the <hi>Dutch</hi> vſed in alledging it ſo, alreadie diſcouered in the anſwer of the <hi>Dutch Relation</hi> (which by this very touch appeareth to be the worke of the ſame Penne that wrote this <hi>Remonſtrance</hi>) that preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded voluntary confeſſion hath not one word or menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Iapons</hi> in it: And yet this <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5711:53"/>
thus ſtoutly prooued this point) triumpheth ouer the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation; ſaying, that theſe contrarieties and diſſimulations ſhew that the ſame marueylouſly ſtrayeth and wandreth from the truth; and that the contrary thereof in all points may be taken for true.</p>
                  <p>After this, the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> commeth to the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> priſoners, ſet downe in our Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/>: and promiſeth that the particulars thereof ſhall hereafter in time be refuted, and prooued vtterly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfe it in the moſt ſubſtantiall points: as ſhall likewiſe that which is there related of the tortures. But why haue they not all this while made, or at leaſt attempted ſome diſproofe hereof? Why could not <hi>Maerschalcke</hi> (whom they haue now depoſed in other points) haue ſaid ſomething to theſe; being himſelfe the ſecond perſon in the Councell, and acquainted with all that paſſed? Well, ſince they be prooued here by ſixe Witneſſes, let them yet ſtand for true, vntill this promiſed Counterproofe arriue.</p>
                  <p>But for the point of torture, the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth in the <hi>Interim,</hi> that if the caſe lawfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, it is no fault in the Iudge to examine vpon the torture: being the Cuſtome in all <hi>Europe,</hi> and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in the <hi>Low Countryes.</hi> And if any were tortured, that was done vpon pregnant and waightie <hi>Indicia,</hi> proofes and confeſſions of others.</p>
                  <p>This hath beene ſufficiently replyed to in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Anſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation, where it is prooued, firſt that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were not lawfully ſubiect to the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Gouernour of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and therefore vnlawfully tortured. Secondly, that the kinde of torture
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5711:54"/>
vſed, was not agreeable to the Law and Cuſtome of the <hi>Low Countryes:</hi> and laſtly, that there was no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Indicium</hi> for the torturing of the firſt <hi>Iapon,</hi> nor none other proofes or <hi>Indicia</hi> againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but the forced confeſſions of the tortured <hi>Iapons;</hi> which ground of torture is prohibited by their owne Law.</p>
                  <p>Yet further the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> fetch an argument out <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> of this point of the tortures, in iuſtification of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers fact at <hi>Amboyna.</hi> If (ſay they) they would haue drawne confeſſions out of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by tortures; why did not they torture all the <hi>Engliſh?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This riddle is plainely vnfolded by the ſame <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation: where it appeareth, that after they had tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, <hi>Iohnſon, Collins,</hi> and <hi>Clarke;</hi> glad was that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman</hi> that could deuiſe any thing to confeſſe, to pleaſe the <hi>Fiſcall,</hi> and auoyde the torture. Yea, <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rock</hi> prayed to God to aſſiſt him in this kinde. Others asked thoſe that had beene formerly examined, what they had confeſſed; ſaying, they would doe the like, thereby to ſhunne the crueltie of the torture. As for thoſe that were acquitted (as hauing confeſſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) the <hi>Dutch</hi> plot could not reach them. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing laide the conſultation of this pretended conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> where none of theſe foure were vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>New-yeares</hi> day; they had no colour to torture them, whom their owne people that ſtood by, knew to be ſo farre abſent: And no man imagineth that all the <hi>Dutch</hi> that were by at the torture, were priuie to the intention of the Gouernour; who in this caſe was to carry himſelfe ſo, as that he muſt not make the buſines ſo groſſe, that all that ſtood by might vnderſtand it. It ſufficed him that he caught the chiefe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:5711:54"/>
there, and ſuch a number by whoſe example all would afterwards abandon the fatall places.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> gathereth that there was <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> no exceſſe vſed, becauſe ſome of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned; to none other end (forſooth) but to giue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their whole proceedings.</p>
                  <p>This indeed is a point wherein the <hi>Dutch</hi> vſed the quinteſſence of their skill: ſo to handle the matter as that they would ſeeme to mixe clemency with Iuſtice; to make their Proceſſe to paſſe the eaſier and fayrer, both among their owne people there, and after when it ſhould come into <hi>Europe.</hi> But he that will but a little conſider what the <hi>Dutch</hi> Gouernours end and ayme was, will finde, that as he and the <hi>Fiſcall</hi> laboured in all the Proceſſe to reach Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> the chiefe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there; neuer ſatisfying themſelues with any confeſſion that made not him guiltie (as appeareth in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation:) ſo when they had caught him, and ſo many other of the chiefe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there, it was a ſmall matter for them to ſpare a few of the meaner ſort: being aſſured that the execution of the reſt, would be a ſufficient warning for all other <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> euer after to keepe their diſtance farre enough from that place. And this tooke ſo right (according to the intention) that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as well at the <hi>Moluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coes</hi> and <hi>Banda,</hi> as the poore remnant at <hi>Amboyna</hi> forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with vpon the newes of this Tragedy, quitted their Factories in all thoſe Iſlands: chooſing rather to leaue the places and their trade there, then their liues for it. For the <hi>Dutch</hi> had ſpoken loude enough, and plaine enough in this action, for all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to vnderſtand their meaning: who therefore would not ſtay till the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5711:55"/>
chiefe of them alſo were thus cut off, and the reſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed with their life for a prey, and for an argument of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Officers clemencie. But if theſe few <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> were ſaued to this end, in the <hi>Dutches</hi> intention, to giue teſtimony of all their proceedings, as here is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged: Why then doe not the <hi>Dutch</hi> receiue and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of their teſtimony? For theſe all with one month accuſe the <hi>Dutch</hi> to haue proceeded by trechery and moſt execrable iniuſtice in this whole action: although indeed ſome of them that were abſolued, confeſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on oath, that they conceiue the reaſon and end of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in ſparing them, to haue beene in hope that for that fauour they would haue giuen teſtimony on their part, when this buſineſſe ſhould come to be examined here in <hi>Europe:</hi> if yet the cauſe ſhould euer come to be reuiewed here; for ſome of the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Amboyna</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared plainely, that they made accompt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Match would preuent the accompting for this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p>The next point that the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> note in the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> Relation of the examination of the priſoners, is the deſcription of the tortures of <hi>Water and fire:</hi> which (they ſay) is finely and prolixly ſet forth and embeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, to mooue compaſſion, and to inueagle the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to ſwallow the reſt of the errors and vntruths of the Relation. But that, albeit all torture is in it ſelfe rough and harſh; eſpecially ſeemeth ſo to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> becauſe none is vſed in <hi>England,</hi> but in caſes of high treaſon, yet the torture of Water is the moſt gentle, ciuill, and ſafe of all other kindes of torture: onely cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an oppreſſion and anxietie of breathing and reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but no repleniſhing and ſwelling of the dodie,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5711:55"/>
as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation ſetteth it out, &amp;c. Yea that all that the ſaid Relation deliuereth touching theſe Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, is but a bare narration onely without any proofe: or at the moſt is witneſſed but by a very few perſons, and thoſe ſuch, as the cauſe concerneth: in which being themſelues once iudicially conuicted, they may not now be admitted and allowed as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt the Iudge and his proceedings, againſt a Court and Councell of foureteene Iudges, perſons well knowne to be of worth and vertue; and againſt their owne confeſſions legally taken, and confirmed with their owne ſubſcriptions.</p>
                  <p>For reply to all this: firſt, for the deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which is here (ſcoffingly) ſaid to be ſo laboured &amp; adorned, to moue compaſſion, &amp; make an eaſie way for vntruthes; it is remitted to the reader to peruſe &amp; iudg it. It will be found as voyd of this art of painting, as it is of the vntruths which the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſpecifie not, leaſt they ſhould be cleared, as other pretended vntruths are already in this reply. The cauſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> needed no ſuch helpes. The truth of the things deliuered in the whole Relation ſo ſhineth in the meere <hi>Series</hi> and circumſtances of the fact, that it diſdained thoſe borrowed colours, feathers, and traſh, wherwith the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> haue trimmed vp this their anſwere. But it is a ſigne of their penury of matter, that they thus carpe at the ſtyle of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As for the gentleneſſe of their torture of Water; that is alſo left to be iudged; yea euen by the words of this <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> that acknowledgeth it to be an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and ſtopping of the breath: then which what ſtriueth more with the very life of a man, or more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5711:56"/>
the nobleſt and tendereſt parts? It is no maruaile that ſome of their owne <hi>Adventurers</hi> tell theſe Direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in Print, that they can cut of another mans eare, with as little feeling as of an old ſhoe. But our people that haue taſted of this <hi>Water-torture</hi> of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and haue heard thoſe that ſuffred both there make the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, ſay, that this is more terrible &amp; inſupportable for the time, then the torture of fire: how euer the wound of the latter reſteth longer in the fleſh. The ſame men alſo tell vs, (and that vpon their oath) that it is not onely a ſtiffling and oppreſſion of the breath; but alſo a repleniſhing of the body till it be ſwollen and ſtretcht, as in <hi>Clarks</hi> examination is ſet downe: contrary to that, theſe <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> here affirme. Yea, but (ſay they) theſe witneſſes are but a very few, and the ſame alſo parties in this cauſe, and ought not to be heard againſt a Colledge of Iudges, honeſt and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall men, nor againſt their owne former confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. That they are ſo few, wee may thanke the <hi>Dutch</hi> that left vs no more. But all that they haue ſpared vs, agree in one vnanimous and conſtant teſtimony. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can there in this caſe be any other proofe required. What? Would the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> haue vs prooue theſe things by the teſtimony of the <hi>Dutch</hi> that were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in this Proceſſe, and are themſelues guiltie of this maſqued murther? Should we haue brought a Certificate hereof vnder the ſeale of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> with the Gouernour and his Councels hands to it? What other proofe is the nature of the cauſe capeable of, but ſuch as wee bring? And whereas the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> ſay here that our witneſſes are parties, and formerly conuict in the cauſe; they ſeeme to forget, that their owne Acts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5711:56"/>
ſhew, that ſome of them were abſolued expreſſely, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers neuer condemned. As for the Credit of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Iudges, ſo often repeated, it is already exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the beginning of this Reply, as alſo in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation.</p>
                  <p>Finally, for the Declarations and Writings of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> 
                     <hi>Towerſon, Coulſon, Griggs,</hi> and others, ſet downe in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation, theſe <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> ſeeme to doubt whether any ſuch be extant. And for the ſtrange ſignes of the ſtorine, the ſodaine madneſſe and death of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyn,</hi> and the new ſickneſſe at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> following the execution of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which they tearme pretended miracles; they ſay, that the truth can be witneſſed by thoſe that were preſent and about them at the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that no ſuch thing happened. And here they adde, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtirre heauen &amp; earth to conceale and couer this deteſtable fact. But who will ſuppoſe (ſay they) that ſubſtantiall people, (men of approued worth and vertue) would ſhew themſelues ſo impious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane to torture and execute innocent perſons? Much leſſe muſt this be preſumed of a Court of Iudges ſworne and eſtabliſhed.</p>
                  <p>As for the Writings of Maiſter <hi>Towerſon, Coulſon, Griggs,</hi> and others, mentioned in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation (now doubted of by the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi>) wee report vs vnto the Lords of his Maieſties priuie Councell, that haue ſeene them, and to the friends of the parties that know their ſeuerall hands; and laſtly, to the ſame Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings themſelues ſtill extant and kept to be ſhewed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any occaſion. As for the ſignes related, they are ſworne by our men that came thence, and further to be prooued by Letters written, from ſome that then ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5711:57"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5711:57"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:5711:58"/>
and (wee ſuppoſe) doe yet ſerue the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> if they be not ſince dead, whereof no newes is yet come. But what Witneſſe doe the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> bring, that thoſe things ſo ſet downe with their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and ſo the eaſier examined, were not ſo? The truth (ſay they) may be witneſſed by thoſe that were preſent and about the priſoners at the execution. But who be thoſe? Why doth not <hi>Maerschalcke</hi> in his deſperate oath (anon to be examined) atteſt that there was no ſuch matter as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> pretend? Or why ſhall wee reiect our peoples teſtimony, and beleeue theſe <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> without any witneſſe? But wee ſhall haue witneſſes hereafter. In the <hi>Interim</hi> then, let the thing ſo already witneſſed remaine for true, till it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by more and better witneſſes. As for the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> ſtirring heauen and earth, not to conceale or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a deteſtable fact of their owne people (as the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance</hi> ſpeaketh) but to diſcouer a moſt damned practiſe of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and to procure Iuſtice vpon it, they conceiue they are not to be blamed herein: yea that it is their dutie to mooue heauen and earth againſt them, that haue mooued hell againſt Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents.</p>
                  <p>Now for the honeſtie and credit of their Gouernour and Councell at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> a ſtring often harped vpon: although it be euident that there is a great difference of the ſtuffe betweene the Iudges of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iudges in the parts of Chriſtendome: yet the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and credit euen of the beſt Iudges is no ſufficient defence for them againſt ſuch apparant proofes of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, as are extant in this cauſe, euen in the acts of the Proceſſe it ſelfe, as is before declared. For the Iudge
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5711:58"/>
that in his Proceſſe obſerueth not the order preſcribed by the Law, is reputed as a priuate perſon. Otherwiſe indeed, the Iudge is not without proofe to be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue done vniuſtly: but this will not ſerue theſe Iudges. Neither is any partie accuſed, to be preſumed guiltie, without <hi>Indicia</hi> or euidence: but euery man to be preſumed good vntill the contrary be prooued. Which ſhould haue mooued thoſe Iudges of <hi>Amboyna</hi> to haue beene tender and carefull in the <hi>Indicijs</hi> that were made the pretexts to torture the firſt <hi>Iapon:</hi> and not to torture a poore man for asking an vſuall and harmeleſſe queſtion, yea, and needfull in the place of his ſeruice; as is ſhewed in the anſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation. Much more ought they in this reſpect to haue beene tender of taking the extorted confeſſions of the <hi>Iapons,</hi> for a ſufficient <hi>Indicium</hi> againſt Maiſter <hi>Towerſon;</hi> not onely in regard of his qualitie, as being the <hi>Agent</hi> and Cape Merchant for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there; but alſo of his innocent and harmeleſſe, (yea godly) behauiour at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and all his life before. For as he was a man of note, and knowne to moſt men of his qualitie here in <hi>England;</hi> ſo all that knew him (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that were well acquainted with him, whereof there is no ſmall number) ioyne and iumpe in this one opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion &amp; commendations of him, that he was of a moſt faire condition and ſweet diſpoſition, harmeleſſe, and without ſpleene or gall; and (in a word) the vnlikelieſt <hi>Engliſhman</hi> that euer went into the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> to be a plotter or practiſer of ſuch a fact, as he was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> hauing thus finiſhed their anſwere <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="T"/> to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation, affirme that by their deduction
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5711:59"/>
of <hi>Iuly,</hi> and this anſwere, they haue ſufficiently iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the proceedings of their Officers at <hi>Amboyna;</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe <hi>ex abundanti</hi> they produce further euidence out of an atteſtation of Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> their late Gouernour in the <hi>Moluccoes.</hi> Which becauſe it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards againe repeated in ſeuerall Articles, ſhall be there with the reſt anſwered.</p>
                  <p>In the meane time, they appeale to the Lords States <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> generall, whether they haue not by all this giuen ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſatisfaction and cauſe to the <hi>Engliſh Company,</hi> to abate and let fall their ſuit, leauing the blame vpon the Authors of this abhominable conſpiracie (as they call it) and of their owne misfortune. Neuertheleſſe, not daring to goe to tryall of the maine cauſe vpon theſe their allegations and proofes, they pray that there may be no precipitation vſed, but a fit reſpite granted them for the exact enquiry of the truth in the <hi>Indies:</hi> and that in the meane time, they may haue the protection of the Lords States, and all miſunderſtanding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary deductions may ceaſe; at leaſt prouiſionally. For put caſe (ſay they) that their Officers be truely guiltie (as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> pretend) yet they muſt be heard before they can be condemned. And in their opinion (ſay they) the ground of the <hi>Conuſance</hi> of this cauſe muſt come from <hi>Amboyna</hi> to <hi>Battauia,</hi> and thence he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and time conuenient being giuen, there will doubtleſſe come daily more and more cleare proofes and light in the cauſe. As for themſelues, they at laſt plainly confeſſe, that they cannot anſwere the obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and circumſtances alledged and propoſed; but that this muſt and can be done by them onely, whom the cauſe toucheth and concerneth: to wit, their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers at <hi>Amboyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:5711:59"/>Here they renounce all the defence and iuſtification which they haue alreadie made; as impertinent and inſufficient. They might haue done well then to haue ſpared all this labour, and at firſt to haue left the cauſe to them whom it concernes, as the <hi>Engliſh Company</hi> by their Letters requeſted them. As for precipitation in the cauſe, the <hi>Engliſh Company</hi> require none. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Acts of the Councell at <hi>Amboyna</hi> themſelues containe all that can be legally pleaded in iuſtification of the Officers, (for, if in them there be no iuſt ground of the condemnation and execution of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> all ſuperuenient proofes come too late to excuſe the Iudges, euen by their owne Lawes) therefore the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Company</hi> preſume and maintaine, that there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ground ſufficient, out of the ſame Acts, and out of the Treatie, whereof this Proceſſe is a plaine breach, for the Lords States generall by an Act of State pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely to declare the Nullity and Iniuſtice of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. But for the iudiciall proceedings againſt the particular perſons that haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted this vnparareld Iniuſtice: there may be ſuch order and courſe taken, as his Maieſtie and the Lords States ſhall finde the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the cauſe to require. Wherein alſo the greateſt care and expedition that can be vſed for the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the parties, will be no precipitation; conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the manifeſt proofes of their Iniuſtice, appearing in their owne Acts, as is before declared.</p>
                  <p>Hauing finiſhed their prayer to the Lords States <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="W"/> generall, to the effect aforeſaid, the ſcope and drift of all, being onely for <hi>Dilation</hi> and <hi>reſpite</hi> in the cauſe: yet as it were repenting them of their former reare and declination of a preſent tryall they come on a freſh
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5711:60"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:5711:60"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:5711:61"/>
with new proofes, which they affirme to be ſo ſtrong and vigorous, that they are of power, more then ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to giue their Officers an entire diſcharge, and to confound their Aduerſaries: and that without helpe of the points before alledged. And to make good theſe great words, they produce eleuen ſeuerall Articles ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by depoſition of <hi>Laurence Maerschalck</hi> their late Cape Merchant at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and now returned into <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſworne to the ſame Articles before the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> of <hi>Delfe</hi> the 4. of <hi>Nouember</hi> laſt <hi>ſtilo nouo;</hi> whoſe name in this <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> they conceale. Next they annexe the report and depoſition of Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> their late Gouernour at the <hi>Moluccoes,</hi> before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And in the laſt place, they repeate ſome points already by them alledged in this <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> and ſo ſhut vp their whole Worke.</p>
                  <p>For the teſtimony of <hi>Maerschalck,</hi> it is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the generall; that he is a partie, being the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond man of the Councell of <hi>Amboyna:</hi> and therefore what is before ſaid againſt the whole Councell, falleth vpon him in his particular with more enforcement. Neuertheleſſe, this proteſtation againſt his incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency to be a Witneſſe in this cauſe being thus premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; wee will peruſe and examine the particulars of his Atteſtation: yet with this leaue, a little to inuert the order of the Articles, (but without preiudice of the ſubſtance of them) thereby to take all the matter of one nature together, to auoyd prolixitie and needleſſe repetition of the ſame thing in diuers parts of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
                  <p>The firſt, ſecond, and third Articles affirme, that as well the <hi>Iapons</hi> as the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> not onely ſigned their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5711:61"/>
ſeuerall confeſſions with euery of their hands reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, but ioyntly and ſeuerally confirmed and perſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſame, euen out of the fetters and irons, at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſeſſions of the Councell; yea the <hi>Engliſh</hi> three or foure ſeuerall times, without retracting or reuoking or changing of anything: albeit the Gouernour ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly admoniſhed them to alter or reuoke any thing which they had falſly confeſſed through paine or feare &amp;c. But that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhrinking vp their ſhoulders confirmed all they had confeſſed to be true, and craued mercy and not Iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>Theſe impudent fictions are anſwered by that which is already noted concerning the Requiſites and Solen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the Acts of all Courts of Iuſtice: which by preſcript of the Law itſelfe record the paſſages of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Seſſion, with the date thereof. But in all the Acts of the Court of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> (vnleſſe they haue giuen a falſe Copie, which yet were to be taken for true againſt themſelues that ſo falſified it) there is no mention of any more confeſſion then one of euery priſoner, nor of any freedome from fetters, nor of any ſuch admonition by the Gouernour as is here pretended. Beſides the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that are eſcaped, as well thoſe that were abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as the reſt, vtterly deny theſe ſeuerall points to be true. Yea the geſture here added of the contracting or ſhrinking vp the ſhoulders, being no <hi>Engliſh</hi> geſture, ſufficiently refuteth this fiction.</p>
                  <p>The fourth Article ſaith, that <hi>William Webber</hi> one of the Complices confeſſed he had receiued a Letter from <hi>Iohn Clarke,</hi> intimating that there was ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary matter and of great importance in hand by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Amboyna:</hi> and that <hi>Iohn Clarke</hi> confeſſed to haue written ſuch a Letter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:5711:62"/>The confeſſion of <hi>Webber</hi> touching this Letter, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation: but whereas this depoſition ſaith, that <hi>Clarke</hi> alſo confeſſed the writing of ſuch a Letter, the Acts themſelues wherein <hi>Clarks</hi> confeſſion is ſet downe by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Actuary, refuteth it, not making mention of any ſuch thing, nor of any queſtion miniſtred to <hi>Clarke</hi> touching this Letter, or his meaning by that intimation; Which would not haue beene omitted, if the <hi>Fiſcall</hi> had not perceiued that <hi>Webber</hi> had faigned this matter onely to auoyde torture.</p>
                  <p>The fifth Article being of the ſame nature with the eighth and ninth, ſhall be anon with them anſwered.</p>
                  <p>The ſixth and ſeauenth Articles recite certaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended voluntary confeſſions of <hi>Thompſon</hi> made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome of the Councell apart: to wit, that he had endured ſo much torture without confeſſion, becauſe he was often vpbraided by Maſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> with drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, and warned that he ſhould not in his cupps diſcouer the pretended plott. Whereupon he had vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſworne to himſelfe, that he would not be the third nor yet the fourth man that confeſſed: what euer torture he ſuffered. But afterwards he confeſſed (ſaith the ſeuenth Article) that he was glad that God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed the fact, for the ſauing of innocent bloud, and that he had doubly deſerued death: yet craued mercy. Here let the courſe of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in making <hi>Affidauit</hi> of the pretended voluntary confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Maiſter <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> before ſix of the Councell apart (and entred into the Acts) be conſidered, as it is truely ſet downe in the anſwere to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation: and it will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appeare, that this confeſſion of <hi>Thomſons</hi> (if any
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5711:62"/>
ſuch had beene) was of much more importance to the clearing of the <hi>Dutch</hi> proceedings, then thoſe obſcure words of Maiſter <hi>Towerſon:</hi> and ſo would the rather haue beene brought by way of Atteſtation into the Acts, as the other were. But in the Acts there is no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of any ſuch confeſſion of <hi>Thomſon:</hi> who alſo going to the execution, and being reproched to be a <hi>Schellam</hi> or villaine, openly and boldly anſwered, that he was as honeſt as the Gouernor himſelfe, and by and by tooke his death that he was innocent.</p>
                  <p>The fifth, eighth, and ninth Articles affirme, that <hi>Collins</hi> confeſſed all without torture, and being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted with Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> before the Councell, auerred his confeſſion, and perſwaded him to doe the like, alſo that Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> being another time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Councell with the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, reproached them with their drunkenneſſe and diſordered liues, and imputed the diſcouery of the conſpiracie to Gods iudgement vpon their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: yet that at laſt Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> confeſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be the Author and inſtigator of the reſt, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them forgiueneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Of all theſe matters being farre more pregnant (if they were true) to haue beene the ground of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence then any thing entred in the Acts, there is no one word or mention in all the Proceſſe, although theſe things are here affirmed to haue paſſed before the bodie of the Councell. But it ſeemeth that <hi>Maerschalk</hi> (ſince his arriuall in <hi>Holland</hi>) is ſhewed the defects of the Proceſſe, and ſo would ſupply them by his owne teſtimony. But he commeth now too late to make new Acts, after the Copie of the Proceſſe imparted to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5711:63"/>
                     <hi>Engliſh.</hi> In particular, <hi>Collins</hi> was tortured with <hi>water</hi> in ſuch ſort, as the view of him afterwards made <hi>Coulſon</hi> confeſſe without torture, as is ſet downe in the <hi>Engliſh Relation,</hi> and yet auerred by thoſe alſo that ſaw him come out as <hi>Coulſon</hi> did. Further, how ſenceleſſe had the ſpeech of Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> beene, to impute the diſcouerie of the plott, to Gods iuſtice vpon the bad life of his pretended Complices, and not rather vpon himſelfe for being the inuenter and Author of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, in it ſelfe more haynous, then any thing he could charge the reſt withall? Laſtly, it is already ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prooued by more competent witneſſes then <hi>Maerschalk,</hi> that Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> and the reſt were neuer together before the Councell, from the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion vntill the laſt ſentence: and that in all that time, he ſpake with none of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but <hi>Coulſon, Griggs,</hi> and <hi>Fardo;</hi> ſo impudent is this atteſtation of <hi>Maerschalck,</hi> that he vſed the ſpeeches here pretended, vnto <hi>Collins</hi> and the reſt; and that before the Councell.</p>
                  <p>The tenth Article ſaith, there was a Letter written by Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> to <hi>Coulſon,</hi> charging him to be the prime and ſole cauſe that mooued him to this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe of making himſelfe Maiſter of the Caſtle: and that the ſame Letter was in the hands of the Gouernor of <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If this be true, how could Maiſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> make himſelfe the firſt author of this conſpiracy, as the Acts and <hi>Maerschalcks</hi> owne relation in the former Articles preſent him? How cometh it, that there is no mention of this Letter in the Acts, nor the ſame Letter or any authenticall Copie thereof ſent ouer for iuſtification of the cauſe, being ſo pregnant and pertinent a proofe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:5711:63"/>The 11. Article telleth a tale of <hi>Collins</hi> his refuſing to ſit and eate with the <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants in their paſſage from <hi>Amboyna</hi> to <hi>Iaccatra</hi> in the ſhippe, when he and <hi>Beamont</hi> were ſent thither: vpon ſcruple (forſooth) to eate with ſuch honeſt men, being himſelfe a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
                  <p>This as it is friuolous and of no value in itſelfe, <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> being then as a condemned man to ſtand to the mercy of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Generall at <hi>Iaccatra:</hi> ſo the truth of it is vtterly denied by <hi>Beamont</hi> that paſſed with him in the ſame ſhippe, and together with <hi>Collins</hi> did eate at the ſame Table with the <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants without ſtrayning of any curteſie for the matter.</p>
                  <p>But to helpe the teſtimony of <hi>Maerschalk,</hi> that ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> all the former points in his owne cauſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the very Acts themſelues, and all other proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities: the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> in the next Article, ſupply him with a <hi>Conteſtis,</hi> beyond exception as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend: to wit, Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> their late Gouernour in the <hi>Moluccoes.</hi> Who comming thence to <hi>Amboyna</hi> after the execution, heard and ſaw ſome things pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to this buſineſſe; whereof, (being now returned into <hi>Holland</hi>) he maketh report and depoſition, in ſixe ſeuerall points, <hi>viz:</hi> Firſt, that it was firmely and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion or doubt beleeued at <hi>Amboyna</hi> generally, and by euery man in particular; yea by himſelfe alſo: that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iapons</hi> there had truely and in effect conſpired the taking of the Caſtle. Secondly, that the ſaid Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> comming through <hi>Hitto, George Sherrock</hi> (one of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Complices) fell at his feete, and acknowledged the great fauour that Gouernour <hi>Speult</hi> and the Councell at <hi>Amboyna</hi> had done him in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5711:64"/>
pardoning his delict. Thirdly, that he was afterwards preſent at <hi>Iaccatra</hi> when <hi>Iohn Beamont</hi> (another of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Complices) confeſſed his fault before the <hi>Dutch</hi> Generall <hi>Carpentiere,</hi> and craued mercy for the ſame. Fourthly, that himſelfe and diuers others at <hi>Iaccatra,</hi> had good and ſure information and notice, that <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> freely confeſſed the conſpiracie alſo to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſident there; but that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon lockt him vp cloſe from ſpeaking with any man; thereby to preuent the diſhonor of the treaſon. Fiftly, that the Gouernour <hi>Speult</hi> is reputed for a man of worth, honorable and godly, by all that haue conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with him: and the reſt of the Councell alſo, ſuch as cannot any way be doubted or ſuſpected guiltie of ſo foule a fact, as to accuſe or miſvſe the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> much leſſe to put them to death, if they had not beene guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Laſtly, that the torture of Water is alwayes vſed by the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and is not ſo cruell nor dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, as other kindes of torture vſed in the <hi>Low Countryes,</hi> and in all <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that were ſaued from the butchery of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> doe not yet beleeue, that Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> hath depoſed, as is here inferred. For when he was at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and laboured to be brought in <hi>expoſt facto,</hi> for the ſaluing of the buſineſſe; he openly profeſſed: that he would waſh his hands of it, and that <hi>Harman van Speult</hi> had begun it, and <hi>Harman van Speult</hi> ſhould end it. And this preſumption of theirs is further confirmed by the manner of citing this Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur <hi>Houtman,</hi> euen in this Article, where his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is not ſimply and clearely alledged; but with this doubtfull variation: <hi>Les dires et depoſitions du Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur Gouerneur Houtman, &amp;c.</hi> Neither is it ſpecified,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5711:64"/>
where or before whom or when he tooke his oath: which yet is according to the Cuſtome ſet downe touching the depoſition of <hi>Maerschalck:</hi> to wit, that he tooke his oath before the <hi>Senate</hi> of <hi>Delft</hi> the 4. of <hi>Nouember</hi> 1624. But admit he be ſworne to theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles: let vs examine their particular import. The firſt is onely of a common opinion and fame that he found at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> that it was a true treaſon. Is it any maruaile that the <hi>Dutch,</hi> that had made the people beleeue that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> meant to haue ript vp the bellies of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with childe (euen of the Natiues) and to make choice by the beautie and feature of the ſeuerall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, which to ſaue and which to ſlay, had prepared a ſufficient rumor againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Signeur <hi>Hout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> to winne his opinion to their cauſe? Next, it is not likely that he ſpake with any, but thoſe of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: who were moſt of them parties in this but cherie: and therefore would make no report to him, but what ſerued their owne turnes. Further, the iudgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed againſt our people, their fact (though neuer done) might be preſumed notorious in Law: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no maruaile he and others gaue credit to it. Yet who knoweth not, that much falſe iudgement happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, notwithſtanding the notorietie induced by the Acts and ſentence? It were an eaſie matter for a Iudge to anſwere any Iniuſtice thus. But when the iudgement and the Iudges are queſtioned of Iniuſtice, the notorie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that themſelues haue made is no plea for them. Yet if the Acts containe ſufficient proofes for ground of the ſentence, then ſuch notorietie may helpe them. But in this caſe, the Acts ſhewing that they haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded contrary to Law, inferre their Iniuſtice to be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5711:65"/>
notorious, as is before ſhewed. For the ſecond and third Articles, concerning <hi>Sherrock</hi> and <hi>Beamonts</hi> confeſſion of their faults <hi>extra</hi> iudicially, and while they were yet in danger: they are of no moment, to prooue their guilt, much leſſe the guilt of thoſe that were executed, of whom theſe confeſſions make no mention; nor eſpecially can they giue any ſuccour to the cauſe of the Gouernour and Councell for their proceedings: who ought to haue had the grounds of their ſentence in the Acts of the Proceſſe, before they condemned and executed our people. More particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, <hi>Sherrock</hi> indeed confeſſeth, that with humble o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyſance he complained to Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> of the <hi>Dutches</hi> daily reproaching him with treaſon, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him that he would deale with the Gouernor <hi>Speult,</hi> to take order with them for their inciuilitie. For (ſaid he) although I had beene guiltie, yet being now par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, why ſhould they thus reproach me? Other confeſſion then this, he vtterly denieth to haue made to Signeur <hi>Houtman. Beamont</hi> alſo confeſſeth, that when he came to <hi>Iaccatra,</hi> being ſent thither to ſtand to the mercy of the Generall; who then told him, that he came thither to die; he was much amaſed. But when ſodainly the Generall in better earneſt told him, he forgaue him; then he gaue him humble, and open thanks; but made no confeſſion of his fault, nor was by the Generall vrged in the leaſt thereunto. For the fourth point, that Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> and others had ſuch notice, as is here pretended of <hi>Beamonts</hi> confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſident; who alſo clapt him vp for it: it were here requiſite that Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> (if he haue thus atteſted) did name his Authors if he will be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5711:65"/>
beleeued. For himſelfe is but <hi>teſtis ex auditu.</hi> In the meane time, not onely <hi>Beamont</hi> denyeth theſe things, but <hi>Collins</hi> that lodged in the ſame chamber at <hi>Iaccatra</hi> with him, auerreth, that his reſtraint and cloſe cuſtody is vtterly feigned; neither did he euer heare any word or inckling of ſuch his confeſſion to the Preſident. Maiſter <hi>Auguſtine Spalding</hi> alſo then one of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Councell at <hi>Iaccatra,</hi> (but now returned into <hi>England</hi>) giueth the like report. For the fifth point, being the faire teſtimony of Signeur <hi>Houtman</hi> touching the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his brother Gouernor, <hi>Van Speult,</hi> and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell; It is a point of ciuilitie in him, to helpe them with a good word in the generall: but it is farre too light to lay in the ſcoale againſt the ſeuerall and preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant proofes of their foule Iniuſtice, before in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply at large ſpecified, by the witneſſe of all our <hi>Engliſh</hi> that were ſaued (as well thoſe that were abſolued as the reſt) by cleare circumſtances of the whole buſineſſe, and by the Acts themſelues of the Councell of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna.</hi> Laſtly, for the Water torture, it appeareth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Signeur <hi>Houtmans</hi> teſtimony, to be vſed by the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>Indies.</hi> The poore <hi>Polarones</hi> and the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> witneſſe it with a miſchiefe. But to make it lawfull; it ſhould be prooued to be vſed in the <hi>Low Countryes:</hi> as hath beene alreadie ſhewed. But why doth Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur <hi>Houtman,</hi> nor the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> in all this diſcourſe ſay nothing for the Fire-torture, which was alſo vſed, and that in moſt barbarous manner and degree vpon the poore <hi>Iapons,</hi> and diuers of the <hi>Engliſh?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> hauing thus preſſed the teſtimony of <hi>Maerschalck</hi> and Signeur <hi>Houtman,</hi> in the next place (being the 13. Article) telleth vs without any witneſſe:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5711:66"/>
that diuers perſons (which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth) to be tortured with Fire and Water, were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer once touched.</p>
                  <p>If this were true and certaine, it had beene eaſie for the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> to haue named the perſons touching whom ſuch error is committed. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation nameth none but <hi>Iohnſon, Thomſon,</hi> and <hi>Clarke</hi> to be tortured with Fire. Which of theſe will the <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants</hi> denie to be ſo handled: againſt ſuch cleare eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our part?</p>
                  <p>The foureteenth Article promiſeth, that the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars and pettie matters (as they are here tearmed) ſhall be diſprooued by the depoſitions of thoſe that were in preſence, and ſhould haue knowne them if any had beene. Therefore vntill they be thus diſprooued, (which will neuer be) let them remaine for true; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being alreadie prooued by the oath of credible perſons, and carrying truth in the very circumſtances.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, for the extraordinary ſignes that happened at the time of the execution, which are here (ſcoffing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) tearmed miracles, the ſame are alſo prooued by oath, and further by Letters written from ſome of the ſeruants of the <hi>Dutch</hi> themſelues at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> readie to be exhibited vpon occaſion. And as it had beene a ſillie part of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to haue feigned ſuch matter, ſo is it no leſſe impudence to deny that which ſo many as well <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> as <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſaw, and knew to be notorious.</p>
                  <p>After all this new charge ſo confidently giuen, yet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Y"/> the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> fall off againe, and not deſiring to put the triall of the cauſe vpon theſe, nor all the reſt of their allegations; they returne by way of concluſion to pray
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5711:66"/>
the Lords States Generall, that there may be a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient reſpite giuen for the better examination of the whole matter: and to that end that they will mediate with his Maieſtie, to content himſelfe alſo therewith.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt India Companie</hi> vpon the grounds before at large deduced, doubt not but that the cauſe will appeare as well to his Maieſty as the Lords States, to be ripe and readie for ſuch an Act of State as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and for the apprehenſion of the Authors of this odious and execrable Proceſſe, as ſoone as they, or any of them can be gotten. And then the iudiciall Proceſſe againſt them may follow, as ſhall appertaine to ſo foule and infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall a Fact. (⸪)</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
